<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse of ecclesiastical lawes and supremacy of the kings of England, in dispensing with the penalties thereof by Mr. Philip Nye.</title>
            <author>Nye, Philip, 1596?-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 127 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52594</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1490A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R41353</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">31355141</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 31355141</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110329</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52594)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110329)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1749:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse of ecclesiastical lawes and supremacy of the kings of England, in dispensing with the penalties thereof by Mr. Philip Nye.</title>
                  <author>Nye, Philip, 1596?-1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W. Cross,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXXVII [1687]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church and state --  England.</term>
               <term>Divine right of kings.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110329:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE OF <hi>Eccleſiaſtical LAWES,</hi> And SUPREMACY of the KINGS OF ENGLAND, In DISPENSING with the PENALTIES thereof.</p>
            <p>By Mr. <hi>PHILIP NYE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>W. Croſs,</hi> MDCLXXXVII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:110329:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:110329:2"/>
            <head>A Diſcourſe of Eccleſiaſtical Laws and Supremacy of the Kings of <hi>ENGLAND,</hi> in diſpenſing with the Penalties thereof.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> The CASE and STATE of the Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ESTION.</head>
               <p>THE <hi>Kings</hi> Power and <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> in <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Affairs may fall under a threefold Conſideration, as 1. Put forth by <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</hi> 2. By <hi>Commiſſion</hi> granted to <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Perſons, and exerciſed in thoſe <hi>Courts</hi> we term <hi>Spiritual,</hi> or <hi>Eccleſiaſtical.</hi> 3. As <hi>ſuch</hi> Affairs are managed and ordered by him in <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and by the <hi>Authority</hi> thereof.</p>
               <p>The form in which theſe <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Lawes are expreſſed to us, is this; <hi>Be it enacted by the King's moſt excellent Majeſty, by and with the advice and conſent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons in Parliament aſſembled, and by the Authority of the ſame,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Merely to <hi>adviſe</hi> and <hi>conſent</hi> implys no more <hi>Authority</hi> in Eſtabliſhment of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Lawes than what was put forth by the <hi>Convocation</hi> in their <hi>Canons;</hi> but it being added <hi>by the Authority</hi> thus mentioned, may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrued either relating to the <hi>advice</hi> and <hi>conſent</hi> of the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> in <hi>Parliament;</hi> which is a <hi>ſuffrage,</hi> and more than <hi>our advice</hi> or bare <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</hi> For it implyeth when <hi>Bills</hi> are formed, read, debated and aſſented to by both <hi>Houſes,</hi> they were then ſtamped with ſome kind of <hi>Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary</hi> authority. Or it is to be <hi>interpreted</hi> as relating to <hi>King, Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons;</hi> which is likely: for Conſultations of <hi>Parliament,</hi> altho conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by <hi>Vote,</hi> yet become not formally a <hi>Law</hi> until His <hi>Majeſty</hi> hath given his <hi>Royal</hi> aſſent.</p>
               <p>And in this ſenſe <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Lawes and Orders, which are enacted and eſtabliſhed by <hi>Statutes,</hi> have as formal a <hi>Sanction,</hi> (being not only by the Authority of the <hi>King;</hi> but by <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> aſſembled in <hi>Parliament</hi>) as other <hi>Lawes</hi> wherein our <hi>Civil</hi> intereſts are concerned, namely, by a joint and not the ſingle Power of either.</p>
               <p>This being granted, ſome may ſay, 'tis then needleſs to diſpute thoſe higher intereſts; and thence alſo inferred, That as theſe <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Lawes have their <hi>riſe,</hi> vigour and ſtrength; ſo their diminution and abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:110329:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>from conjunction of both Powers, and are more fixed and ſtable than thoſe <hi>Canons</hi> and <hi>Orders</hi> in <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Matters that have their <hi>ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> from the King only.</p>
               <p>But to this I ſay briefly, theſe <hi>Powers</hi> are not ſo equal but the <hi>King</hi> hath the <hi>Supremacy,</hi> and is enabled thereby to ſuch <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Orderings</hi> about the <hi>Penalties</hi> of our <hi>Lawes</hi> as are <hi>peculiar</hi> to the <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>Dignity</hi> of a <hi>King:</hi> as in <hi>mitigating, exempting, diſpenſing, licenſing, pardoning,</hi> &amp;c. and all this more eſpecially in Matters <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> as by the following will appear.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Superiority</hi> exerciſed by the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>England</hi> with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the <hi>Penalties</hi> of our <hi>Lawes</hi> both <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> and <hi>Civil</hi> ſhall be ſpoken to in theſe two particulars.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> That ſuch an <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>Supremacy</hi> is neceſſary, and <hi>ought</hi> to be placed in ſome <hi>hand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> That it is a <hi>Dignity</hi> which hath been always in the <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Queens</hi> of this <hi>Realm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. For the <hi>former.</hi> In all <hi>Polities</hi> and <hi>Forms</hi> of <hi>Government,</hi> as there is a <hi>rule</hi> the which is to be the <hi>meaſure</hi> to and by which all mens actions that live under that <hi>Polity</hi> are <hi>ordinarily</hi> to be Conformed and Judged; ſo is there always ſome <hi>proviſion</hi> made for mitigating the <hi>rigour</hi> of the <hi>rule</hi> in <hi>Caſes</hi> which <hi>may</hi> fall out and cannot be foreſeen by the wiſeſt <hi>Legiſlators:</hi> And in ſuch <hi>caſes</hi> to exerciſe <hi>ſummum jus</hi> would be <hi>ſumma injuria.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is here not only a <hi>Power</hi> to <hi>Judge</hi> as the <hi>Caſe</hi> ſtands in the ſtrict <hi>Letter</hi> of the <hi>Law;</hi> but as there are <hi>Courts</hi> of <hi>Law,</hi> ſo are there <hi>Chanceries,</hi> Courts of <hi>Equity</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi> wherein the <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Rule</hi> it ſelf is <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed</hi> with, and <hi>varied</hi> from. The Proceedings there are not according to the <hi>ſtrict</hi> terms of the <hi>Law,</hi> but <hi>ſecundum aequum &amp; bonum,</hi> according as the <hi>merits</hi> of the <hi>Caſe</hi> require.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For <hi>Lawes</hi> conſtituted for a whole <hi>Nation</hi> univerſally to be ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto by Perſons of what quality ſoever, and how much ſoever diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in their Conditions, muſt needs in their <hi>ſtrict</hi> execution bear harder upon ſome men than upon others. Parliaments in their Lawes going by the <hi>rule</hi> of <hi>ad ea quae frequentius accidunt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>better a miſchief than always an inconvenience.</hi> It is taken for granted that a general <hi>Law</hi> which hath its good and neceſſity in reſpect to the <hi>bulk</hi> and <hi>body</hi> of a People, may prove unequal to particular Perſons from the Circumſtances of their Condition. In the Common-wealth the eaſe and benefit of each particular perſon of what degree or condition ſoever is to be conſulted; but where <hi>Lawes</hi> are executed in their full <hi>rigour,</hi> and no particular Mercy or Indulgence in ſpecial and unuſual Caſes, it will not be. So <hi>God</hi> himſelf who knows every man's heart, yet ſome of his <hi>Lawes</hi> which are given in the general to all, would not prove ſo equal to each at all times without <hi>exemptions</hi> in particular Caſes. Hence we ſay <hi>affirmative Precepts bind not AD
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:110329:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>SEMPER.</hi> To ſuch <hi>Lawes</hi> is that of <hi>Mark, C.</hi> 2 to be referred in the <hi>Caſe</hi> of the <hi>Shew-bread.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the <hi>Pope</hi> who aſſumes to himſelf a poſſibility not to Erre, yet how doth his Republic abound in <hi>Courts</hi> for <hi>Faculties, Diſpenſation, Indulgences?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. It is alſo to be Conſidered, there are no Societies of men but may <hi>erre</hi> in their counſels. <hi>Lawes</hi> made in one <hi>Parliament</hi> come to a review, and often to an alteration, yea to a <hi>repeal</hi> in the next. The <hi>intervals</hi> of thoſe great <hi>Councels</hi> are ſome time long, and if no way of relief were in the mean time, the <hi>Subject</hi> would without remedy undergo the Penalty of an unequal Law.</p>
               <p>Theſe and the like Conſiderations make it neceſſary that beſides the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlative</hi> Power placed in the <hi>Parliament,</hi> there be ſome hand or other alſo by which upon all <hi>emergent</hi> occaſions, the <hi>rigour</hi> of a <hi>Law</hi> as to its <hi>Penalty</hi> may be abated, by the means whereof not only mens Liberties and Eſtates but lives alſo are ſometimes preſerved.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For the other, This <hi>balance</hi> hath always been <hi>truſted</hi> in the hand of and annexed to the Sovereign <hi>Majeſty</hi> of every State.</p>
               <p>For this intereſt doth little vary, but remaineth in a manner the ſame in all States in what <hi>form</hi> ſoever they be eſtabliſhed. In the <hi>State</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> being an <hi>Empire,</hi> and its <hi>Crown</hi> in many <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> (eſpecially relating to <hi>theſe</hi> Matters ſtyled <hi>Imperial</hi>) this Power is <hi>inſeparably</hi> annexed thereunto; which needs little proof, it being confirmed by the OATH of SUPREMACY. Our great <hi>Lawyers</hi> alſo give in their <hi>ſuffrage</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, frequently affirming that the <hi>Statutes</hi> relating to the King's <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical</hi> Juriſdiction are not <hi>introductive</hi> of <hi>new,</hi> but <hi>declarative</hi> of the <hi>old</hi> Lawes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When an Act</hi> (ſay theſe two learned Judges <hi>Coke</hi> and <hi>Rolls</hi>) <hi>forbiddeth under a Penalty, in caſe it may be inconvenient unto diverſe particular perſons in reſpect to Circumſtances, the Law gives Power to the King to diſpenſe therewith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in like <hi>Caſes,</hi> or upon <hi>other</hi> Conſiderations equal, <hi>he</hi> may <hi>diſpenſe, licenſe, pardon,</hi> &amp;c. yea althô theſe <hi>Lawes</hi> have been paſſed by His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty's <hi>royal</hi> aſſent formerly, and (what is more) a <hi>Clauſe</hi> inſerted in the <hi>Act</hi> that <hi>the King's Licence in this or that caſe ſhall be void.</hi> Yet it will be no <hi>BARR to</hi> ſuch <hi>Prerogatives as are originally</hi> and <hi>inſeparably inherent</hi> in his <hi>royal Perſon,</hi> but he may give <hi>Licence</hi> with a <hi>NON OBSTANTE</hi> thereunto.</p>
               <p>A learned <hi>Sergeant</hi> in his <hi>NO MOTECHNIA</hi> hath theſe words, <hi>The King by a Clauſe of NON OBSTANTE may diſpence with a Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute Law, if he recite the Statute, though the Statute ſay ſuch Diſpenſation ſhall be merely void. And he may licence things forbidden as to Coin money, which is made by the Statute Capital, and was before unlawful, for that is but</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum Prohibitum; <hi>but</hi> malum in ſe, <hi>as to leave a Nuiſance in the High way,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:110329:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>he cannot licenſe to do, but when it is done he may pardon it; but where the Statute ſaith</hi> his Licence ſhall be void (<hi>which the Civilians call</hi> clauſula de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative) <hi>there it muſt have a Clauſe of NON OBSTANTE</hi> (i.e.) <hi>NOTWITHSTANDING ANY STAT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TE, and elſe it is not good.</hi> And (ſaith the ſame <hi>Author</hi>) <hi>he may in reſpect of his Supreme Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Juriſdiction, exempt ſome from the Juriſdiction of the Ordinary, and diſpenſe with others in things which the Eccleſiaſtical Law Prohibits upon the ſame ground that they are not,</hi> mala in ſe, <hi>but</hi> prohibita.</p>
               <p>I hold clear, ſaith Judge <hi>Hobart,</hi> That <hi>thô the Statute ſaith, that all Diſpenſations, &amp;c. ſhall be granted in manner and form following, that yet the King is not thereby reſtrained, but his Power remaineth full and perfect as before, and he may ſtill grant them as King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The King may remitt the Penalty and Puniſhment thô not diſpenſe where what is forbidden by Law is</hi> malum in ſe, ſaith that <hi>Sergeant</hi> in his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned <hi>Diſcourſe:</hi> much more then where what is forbidden is but <hi>malum Prohibitum.</hi> The <hi>Statute</hi> indeed of 1 <hi>Ed.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. Enacts that no <hi>letter</hi> ſhall <hi>proceed</hi> from the <hi>King</hi> to diſcharge an <hi>excommunicated</hi> Perſon, but where the <hi>King's Liberty</hi> is <hi>prejudiced:</hi> but as this <hi>Statute</hi> it ſelf proves the <hi>late</hi> and <hi>former</hi> practice, ſo it takes it not away, ſince the <hi>King's liberty</hi> of diſcharging ſuch Perſons uſed before is preſerved by the ſame <hi>Statute.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of the Prerogative and Regal Power in relation to Eccleſiaſtical Lawes and Matters of Religion.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>REligion</hi> in the <hi>moral</hi> part thereof, namely, the <hi>Precepts</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> the inſtitutions and <hi>Ordinances</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> theſe are not ſubject to any humane Wiſdom or Power. The <hi>Apoſtles</hi> that were of higher <hi>authority</hi> in theſe <hi>Affairs</hi> than any on earth, went no further then as 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23. <hi>What I have received of the Lord that I deliver unto you.</hi> To make <hi>Lawes</hi> in <hi>Spiritual</hi> Matters that are ſuch by the <hi>Light</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> that men may be moved to do and act according to this <hi>Light</hi> in duty and our <hi>Civil</hi> concerns, we yield unto the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> who is <hi>cuſtos utriuſque tabulae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. There are <hi>matters</hi> of <hi>Circumſtance:</hi> alſo theſe and the like are made by our Lawes to depend upon the <hi>power</hi> and <hi>ordering</hi> of the <hi>Prince.</hi> This <hi>diſtinction</hi> you have laid down as <hi>Law</hi> by <hi>Judge Hobart.</hi> Theſe are his words: <hi>Though it be</hi> jure divino <hi>that Chriſtian People be provided of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian offices and duties, as of Teaching, Adminiſtration of Sacraments, and the like, and of Paſtors for that purpoſe, and therefore to debar them wholy of it,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:110329:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>were expreſly againſt the Law of God: Yet the diſtinction of Pariſhes, and the form of furniſhing every Pariſh Church with its proper Curate, Rector or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor by the way of Preſentation, Inſtitution, &amp;c. as it is uſed diverſly in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Churches, and the ſtate or title which he hath or is to have in his Church and Benefice, is not a poſitive Law of God in point of Circumſtance. And we know well that the Primitive Church in its greateſt Purity, was but voluntary Congregations of Believers ſubmitting themſelves to the Apoſtles, and after to other Paſtors, to whom they did miniſter of their Temporals as God did move them. Government</hi> is a <hi>beam</hi> of Divine Power, and therefore he <hi>proceeds</hi> ſaying, <hi>if a People refuſe all Government, it were againſt the Law of God, but if a popular State will receive a Monarchy, it ſtands well with the Law of God.</hi> In the <hi>Caſe</hi> of <hi>Glover</hi> and <hi>Colt</hi> againſt the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Coventry</hi> and <hi>Litch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi> pag. 149.</p>
               <p>From all this the <hi>Judge</hi> ſeems to confirm his <hi>diſtinction</hi> by way of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon</hi> thus. As in <hi>humane</hi> affairs <hi>Government</hi> in the general and <hi>eſſentials</hi> of it, that <hi>one man be ſubject to another in an orderly way,</hi> is neceſſary, and <hi>jure divino,</hi> and not in man's <hi>liberty</hi> and <hi>diſpoſe:</hi> Yet for the <hi>modes</hi> and <hi>forms</hi> of <hi>Government</hi> and like <hi>Circumſtances,</hi> it is left to the choice and wiſdom of Men and the Conduct thereof.</p>
               <p>So in Matters of <hi>Religion</hi> which are not <hi>jure divino,</hi> our <hi>Law</hi> judgeth the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> hath the ordering thereof in each Nation according to the manners and temper of the People, which is various: And in particular the diſpoſing of <hi>Paſtors</hi> and <hi>People</hi> for the more convenient and orderly Service and Worſhip of God to be only <hi>jure humano,</hi> and may be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and was ſo in the <hi>Primitive</hi> Church in her greateſt <hi>Purity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Paſtors and People were not then as now engaged by this relation one to another in this <hi>Parochial</hi> bond or tye, but enjoyed a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> liberty voluntarily to diſpoſe of themſelves, under ſuch and ſuch a miniſtry as they ſhould make choice of to themſelves. The Church is ſaid in that ſtate to be in greateſt Purity. 1. The <hi>Congregational</hi> way therefore is not a way in this learned <hi>Judge's</hi> opinion of diſorder, and confuſion, as is ſo frequently ſuggeſted. 2. And that it is in the power of Supreme <hi>Majeſty</hi> to <hi>diſpenſe</hi> with a <hi>Pariſhioner</hi> as well as with a <hi>Paſtor</hi> or <hi>Rector</hi> to be a <hi>non-reſident</hi> and take another <hi>Rectory,</hi> the diviſion of Pariſhes being <hi>jure humano.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What thoſe things and Matters of <hi>Religion</hi> are in the judgment of our <hi>State</hi> that come under the manage of <hi>humane</hi> Wiſdom and <hi>Power,</hi> is well expreſſed in Queen <hi>Elizabeth's Advertiſement. Theſe Orders and Rules have been meet and convenient to be uſed and followed; yet not preſcribing theſe Rules as Laws equivalent with the eternal Word of God, and of neceſſity to bind the Conſciences of our Subjects, in the nature of them conſidered in themſelves; or as they ſhould add any efficacy or more holineſs to the virtue of publick Prayers, and to the Sacraments, but as temporal Orders meerly Eccleſiaſtical
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:110329:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>without any vain Superſtition, or as Rules in ſome part of diſcipline, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing decency, diſtinction and order for the time.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in the <hi>Articles</hi> of 1562, <hi>It is not neceſſary that Traditions and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies be in all places one or utterly alike, for at all times they have been diverſe and may be changed according to the diverſity of Countrys and Mens manners: So that nothing be ordained againſt God's Word.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is granted that even theſe <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Lawes ought to be conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Word of God, and to theſe general Rules laid down in the <hi>Scripture</hi> for ordering the Worſhip and Service of God in the Churches; as <hi>let all things be done decently and to edification: Give no offence to Jew or Gentile,</hi> and the like, but not to be mens mere inventions.</p>
               <p>That <hi>diſtinction</hi> which ſome would make of things againſt or contrary, and what is according to the Word of God, as they apply the one to matters of <hi>Faith,</hi> the other to matters of <hi>Order,</hi> is a <hi>diſtinction</hi> without a difference: there is more wit than truth in that interpretation of <hi>Chriſt's words, He that is not with me is againſt me;</hi> and in another place, <hi>He that is not againſt me is with me,</hi> applying one to matters of Faith, the other to matters of Order. There is no ſuch <hi>diſtinction</hi> to be made, but <hi>Rites, Ceremonies,</hi> and matters of <hi>Order</hi> ought to be according to God's Word as well as matters of <hi>Faith.</hi> Magiſtrates are to judge <hi>circa res Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticas, de iis ſi fidei ſint dogmata vel ritus &amp; Ceremeniae: earum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> veritatem &amp; equitatem juxta verbi divini normam. Mocket de Pol. Eccl. Anglicanae</hi> cap. 30. And <hi>the Power of the King ſtands not in forming new Articles of Faith or formes of Religion, and ſuch as were</hi> Jeroboam's <hi>Calves, but in defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and propagating that Faith and Religion of which God in the Scripture is the undoubted Author,</hi> faith <hi>Maſon</hi> of <hi>Biſhops,</hi> cap. 5.</p>
               <p>It is evident thoſe <hi>holy</hi> men our firſt <hi>Reformers</hi> made no ſuch diſtinction; but that all ſhould be done <hi>according</hi> to God's <hi>Word,</hi> laying before them theſe general Rules in <hi>Scripture,</hi> even in retaining that which hath been ſo offenſive; for of the retaining Ceremonies there is this account given by them, <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe <hi>they appertain to Edification: whereunto all things done in the Church,</hi> as the Apoſtle teacheth, <hi>ought to be referred.</hi> And our <hi>Liturgy</hi> ſaith thus: <hi>There is nothing to be read but the very pure Word of God and the Holy Scriptures, or that which is evidently grounded upon the ſame. Preface to the Common-Prayer. God be thanked</hi> (ſaith good King <hi>Edw.</hi> 6.) <hi>we know both by his word what is fit to be reformed and have amended,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The Biſhop of</hi> Rome <hi>and his Juriſdiction is taken away and aboliſhed, becauſe is had no ground or eſtabliſhment in the Lawes of God.</hi> Injunct. <hi>Ed. 6.</hi> So <hi>Pil grimages, Offerings, Beads, Images are done away, being works deviſed by man fancy, and beſide Scripture.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is convenient thus diſtinctly to have inſiſted upon what we term <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> or Matters <hi>Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> according to that ſenſe in which the Civil <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> aſſumes to himſelf the ordering hereof, and what influence
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:110329:5"/>and authority the Scriptures have, or ought to have in theſe <hi>Rites</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and matters of <hi>Orders</hi> as well as matters of <hi>Faith.</hi> For hereby it appears whence it is mens Conſciences are more concerned in theſe <hi>Lawes</hi> than in other <hi>municipal</hi> Lawes of the Nation; and their not being free to ſubmit to theſe <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Lawes when not formed according to <hi>God's</hi> Word, is no evidence of that <hi>Seditious</hi> ſpirit that <hi>kicks</hi> againſt all <hi>Lawes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. There is a <hi>neceſſity,</hi> and that of much greater importance, <hi>Proviſion</hi> be made of <hi>Diſpenſations,</hi> &amp;c. as occaſion ſhall be of Lawes <hi>Eccleſiastical</hi> than <hi>Civil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In Matters of <hi>Religion</hi> and the Service of God, (1.) Multitudes there are of looſe and prophane Perſons, and in reſpect to ſuch neither are the <hi>Lawes</hi> in themſelves, nor in the <hi>execution</hi> of them, ſevere enough. (2.) Againſt <hi>POPISH Recuſants</hi> the <hi>Lawes</hi> have been <hi>ſevere</hi> enough, yet in the <hi>Execution,</hi> great Moderation (3.) There are thoſe (and bleſſed be God great numbers) who are not only Orthodox in Faith, but of unbla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meable life in the greater things of the Law and Goſpel. Theſe have faln under moſt fevere <hi>Lawes,</hi> and of late with greateſt ſeverity put in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and would be utterly ruined, if there be no means of relaxation. It is in the behalf of theſe I argue this Neceſſity of Indulgence, and from theſe and the like Conſiderations.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. There is a greater <hi>proneneſs</hi> in <hi>conſcientious</hi> men to <hi>ſcruple</hi> and to be doubtful in their obedience to the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> than to the <hi>Civil</hi> Lawes of a Nation: as before.</item>
                  <item>2. The great difficulty in forming Lawes wherein mens <hi>Conſciences</hi> are immediately concerned ſo as not to diſſatisfie ſome, if not many.</item>
                  <item>3. If thoſe Lawes be not according to <hi>Scripture</hi> in the apprehenſions of thoſe that are to obey, whatever they are in themſelves, it's our Sin if we obey: it's not ſo in Civil commands.</item>
                  <item>4. It is not of ſo ill conſequence for us to yield obedience to a <hi>Civil</hi> as to an <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Law, if ill conſtituted by the <hi>State.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. From what is found in a manner peculiar in theſe our <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Lawes, and the <hi>adminiſtration</hi> of them many ways prejudicial to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, there is a <hi>neceſſity</hi> ſome ſuch <hi>proviſion</hi> be found on our behalf of this kind.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. The real doubts and <hi>ſcruples</hi> about our obedience in theſe <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Matters, cannot but be more and greater than in other Lawes. A man of the greateſt knowledge in theſe things <hi>knoweth but in part,</hi> and the moſt men have but a <hi>parcel</hi> in this <hi>part.</hi> It is true the Principles and the greater matters of <hi>Religion</hi> are in great perſpicuity laid down in <hi>Scripture,</hi> which <hi>gives knowledge to the Simple;</hi> but theſe matters of <hi>Circumſtance</hi> and external <hi>order</hi> we have for the moſt part in the generals only, and hints from <hi>Examples</hi> and <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> of the Apoſtolical Churches, in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpre.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110329:6"/>terpretation whereof the moſt learned find difficulties and are divided. Now the want of Knowledge is the ground of <hi>ſcruple</hi> and doubts in our practice, 1 <hi>C.</hi> 8.7. For the working of Conſcience is from the ultimate reſolution of the <hi>practical</hi> underſtanding, and hence it is that the ſame Practice may be not only <hi>ſcrupled,</hi> but a Sin to one man, that is not to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon the account of different apprehenſions. There may notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding be <hi>integrity</hi> and ſincerity in both, and therefore they are <hi>ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly</hi> to be dealt with as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> requires, which you read in <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A great difficulty there is to form <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Lawes; they being to be the ſame (where <hi>uniformity</hi> is much ſtood upon) for a whole Nation, ſo as not to leave grounds of diſſatisfaction to many mens apprehenſions, being various thorough the degrees of Light: in ſo much as that may be Sin to <hi>one</hi> man, which is a <hi>liberty</hi> to another of a greater degree of light. A <hi>little</hi> is next to <hi>nothing,</hi> and what is indifferent is neareſt in like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to moral Good or Evil. Hence ſo frequent miſtakings. And as it is with particular Perſons, ſo may it be with a Society or Company of men: one true <hi>Church</hi> in theſe things differing from another, and the ſame Church differing from it ſelf upon further diſcoveries. A <hi>Synod,</hi> a <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> may judge ſuch and ſuch things, that they who are to ſubmit, may ſincerely <hi>ſcruple,</hi> and ſtick at as Sin. If <hi>Churches</hi> and Men <hi>heavenly enlightned</hi> are thus expoſed to vary in their apprehenſions, we cannot be confident of any <hi>Councel</hi> or <hi>Aſſembly</hi> made up of the moſt Wiſe and Prudent Men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Parliaments</hi> are choſen by the <hi>votes</hi> of the <hi>promiſcuous</hi> multitudes in <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect</hi> (we would hope) to their <hi>ſufficiency</hi> in managing our <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral</hi> concernments: but as to their Skill and Ability to diſcern and judge of ſuch matters appertaining to <hi>Order</hi> in the Service and <hi>Worſhip</hi> of God, <hi>all</hi> men have not this <hi>Knowledge:</hi> this is little or not at all attended by thoſe that <hi>Elect</hi> them; by reaſon whereof Matters wherein mens Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences are concerned are not at all times carried by thoſe who are moſt <hi>Conſcientious</hi> in that Aſſembly, who are not alwayes the <hi>Major</hi> part; yet notwithſtanding are required in their Conſciences to aſſent and conſent to ſuch Determinations being made, although poſſibly near one half in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber diſſented in the paſſing of them; and it is unavoidable in all and the beſt Aſſemblies that are choſen by the general <hi>ſuffrage</hi> of a Nation.</p>
               <p>Again, Theſe matters of <hi>Ceremony</hi> and external Order are ſometimes managed in part with reſpect to a Party different in their apprehenſions, and who thereupon form theſe Lawes with reſpect to <hi>Prudence</hi> as well as <hi>Conſcience.</hi> In our <hi>firſt</hi> Reformation it was ſaid <hi>ſuch Superſtitions are taken away, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>time would ſerve quietly to do it,</hi> and many things were left re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining in our <hi>Liturgy,</hi> which otherwiſe would have been removed in compliance with that form of <hi>divine</hi> Service uſed-before by the <hi>Papists,</hi> that they may not be provoked but rather won thereby to our Religion.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:110329:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>Womens <hi>Baptizing</hi> was continued in our <hi>Liturgy,</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter</hi>) elſe the <hi>Book</hi> would not have paſſed the Houſe. [<hi>Conf. at</hi> Hampton-Court.] King <hi>James</hi> was once willing that ſome Ceremonies giving offence ſhould be removed. But the <hi>Parliament</hi> then ſitting thought it not Prudence; and our preſent <hi>Sovereign</hi> would have done a great matter for the Eaſe of Tender Conſciences, as appears by ſome of the <hi>Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> herein after mentioned; but it ſtood not with the <hi>Prudence</hi> of this <hi>Houſe,</hi> as they expreſſed in their Anſwer, without whoſe concurrence His Majeſty thought not fit then to do it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. From <hi>miſtaken</hi> Principles, as <hi>that there can be no <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity without <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, that there can be no Diſcipline in a Church without ſome Ceremonies of humane Inſtitution; that things in Worſhip indifferent become neceſſary, being impoſed by Authority: That things in matters of Order that are once eſtabliſhed, and ſome time continued in the Church may not with ſafety be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered.</hi> Theſe things I offer not to derogate from <hi>Parliaments</hi> in <hi>their manage</hi> of <hi>ſuch</hi> Affairs, but upon this ſerious account only, To ſhew that as our <hi>Civil</hi> Lawes have made proviſion that the <hi>Church</hi> ſhall not in their <hi>Lawes</hi> and <hi>Canons</hi> order <hi>any</hi> thing againſt the <hi>Prerogative</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> or the <hi>Lawes</hi> and <hi>Statutes</hi> of the Realm in general, and <hi>that ſuch Canons ſhall not be in force that do.</hi> (25 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8.19.) So likewiſe <hi>Lawes</hi> and <hi>Statutes</hi> in <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Affairs, eſtabliſhed by the <hi>Civil</hi> Power, if they be found to <hi>derogate</hi> from the <hi>Prerogative</hi> of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> or the <hi>Lawes</hi> and <hi>Statutes</hi> of his <hi>Kingdom</hi> ought not to be in force upon mens Conſciences.</p>
               <p>As <hi>Church-men</hi> being ſuppoſed not to be ſo well underſtood in <hi>ſecular</hi> Lawes but may tranſgreſs, ſo may ſecular <hi>Perſons</hi> likewiſe in their order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings about Church Affairs; therefore there is a like neceſſity of a Power to <hi>review,</hi> Judge and <hi>diſpenſe</hi> with ſuch <hi>Lawes</hi> as ſhall be found to diſturb the <hi>Conſciences</hi> of <hi>peaceable</hi> Subjects, as occaſion may urge thereunto. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. by Commiſſion (which was continued by <hi>Edw.</hi> 6.) <hi>appointed</hi> 32 Perſons, 8 of <hi>each</hi> Profeſſion, to <hi>peruſe</hi> the <hi>Canons</hi> of the <hi>Clergy</hi> then in force, to the end thoſe might be removed that were any ways againſt the <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>State.</hi> Theſe <hi>Kings</hi> might have done the like in reſpect to thoſe <hi>Canons</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Lawes</hi> enacted in <hi>Parliament,</hi> if they were found to dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate from <hi>Chriſt's</hi> Commands, or his <hi>Inſtitutes,</hi> or if <hi>juſtly</hi> offenſive to the peaceably Godly, that <hi>Diſpenſations</hi> might be granted for the preſent, till further <hi>Reformation</hi> be obtained.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>Municipal</hi> Lawes of a Nation are from and conformed to the <hi>Principles</hi> of right <hi>Reaſon</hi> and common <hi>Juſtice</hi> only, and we have ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Reſolutions of thoſe Wiſe and Prudent <hi>Senators</hi> we our ſelves have made choice of to enact and eſtabliſh ſuch <hi>Lawes</hi> for us, and therefore may acquieſce in their Determinations without further <hi>enquiry,</hi> having given a kind of abſolute <hi>pre-conſent</hi> to ſuch Lawes as ſhall be enacted by them: but it is not ſo in Eccleſiaſtical Lawes intruſted with the ſame
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:110329:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>Perſons, for they are to be formed according to God's <hi>Word</hi> which <hi>every</hi> man is to take as his <hi>immediate</hi> Rule, and not to do or ſubmit to any thing in his Practice about the <hi>Notion</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> but what is conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thereunto; he is to <hi>LIVE</hi> and <hi>act</hi> by <hi>his</hi> own <hi>Faith.</hi> To Lawes <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical</hi> therefore made in <hi>Parliament</hi> we give only a <hi>Conditional</hi> Conſent, <hi>viz. So far as they are agreeable to God's Word, and concur with Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rules;</hi> nor is it in the <hi>liberty</hi> of any man's <hi>Conſcience</hi> or reaſon to yield more, nor is there any more by us <hi>intruſted</hi> with the <hi>Repreſentative,</hi> the Parliament. If a man doth <hi>ſcruple</hi> the reaſonableneſs or equity of a <hi>Law</hi> eſtabliſhed concerning <hi>Civil</hi> right, or what is required from ſuch a <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute,</hi> he may notwithſtanding yield <hi>Obedience</hi> without <hi>Sin,</hi> and ought ſo to do, rather than to offend by any appearance of diſobedience as <hi>Christ</hi> himſelf did, <hi>Matth.</hi> 17.26, 27. But in Matters of <hi>Religion,</hi> even Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances Ceremonies or Matters of Order, or the leaſt thing wherein the Lord hath concerned his Word, if there be a doubt or <hi>ſcruple</hi> whether it be lawful and conformable to <hi>Scripture;</hi> tho it be from Ignorance, or weakneſs, yet I ſin if I ſubmit in practice thereof, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.21. <hi>compared</hi> with 2, 3.</p>
               <p>The conſequence of Tranſgreſſion in this kind is more than the loſs of Eſtate, Liberties, yea, of Life it ſelf. If Lawes from Superiors concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Civil</hi> right be unjuſt in themſelves, or prove unequal from the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of this or that man's Caſe, who cannot be relieved by any indulgence, he may ſubmit without Sin, and without tranſgreſſing any Law of God; nay, it is virtue and pleaſing to God to ſhew our <hi>patience</hi> in ſuch <hi>ſuffering,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. compared with 18, 19. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6, 7. but not ſo in the Matters of <hi>Religion;</hi> for we have it from <hi>Chriſt</hi> to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, that is, not to ſubmit <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2.20. and <hi>God</hi> blames his People by his <hi>Prophets,</hi> for willingly <hi>walking</hi> after the <hi>Commandments</hi> and <hi>keeping</hi> the <hi>Statutes of Omri,</hi> Hoſea 5.12. Micah 6.16. <hi>the Lord is a jealous God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. If there be not a Power to <hi>Judge</hi> and <hi>Diſpenſe</hi> intruſted in ſome hand, the People are in a worſe condition on theſe accounts then in their <hi>civil</hi> intereſt, and that upon a threefold account.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Secular <hi>Lawes</hi> and <hi>Statutes</hi> made in behalf of the Subject are often upon further Deliberation and Experience of inconvenience altered and repealed, whereby the Subject hath eaſe. It is ordinarily ſeen in our Civil concerns, that ſome <hi>ACTS</hi> of Parliament that partly for their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, or upon ſome other account, paſſed as doubtful whether fit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main as <hi>ſtanding</hi> Lawes, are therefore limited to a certain Time, and after which to expire and ceaſe. The ſevere <hi>Act</hi> of 35 <hi>Eliz.</hi> which in the Proceſs of it reached mens lives when firſt paſſed, was to remain a Law but to the end of the next <hi>Seſſion</hi> of <hi>Parliament:</hi> which in regard of ſome doubt (it ſeems) whether in force or not, is declared by this preſent Parliament to be ſo, and that it ought to be put in due execution. And
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:110329:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>now at this time there is a <hi>Miniſter</hi> of the Goſpel under the Sentence of that <hi>Act,</hi> and for tranſgreſſing that Law had loſt his life, had not His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty interpoſed by his <hi>Prerogative.</hi> A wiſe <hi>Stateſman</hi> once adviſed and expreſſed himſelf thus: <hi>I ask why the Civil State ſhould be purged and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored with good and wholſom Lawes made in every</hi> 30 <hi>or</hi> 40 <hi>years in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, providing Remedies as faſt as time breedeth Miſchiefs, and comrariwiſe the Eccleſiaſtical State ſhould ſtill continue upon the dreggs of time, and receive no alteration. Now for theſe many years we have heard of no offers of Bills in Parliament, is it becauſe there is nothing amiſs?</hi> [<hi>Sir</hi> Fr. Bacon.]</p>
               <p n="2">2. In that all Proceedings in <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Courts are ever to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt rigour and letter of their <hi>Canons</hi> and Orders. There is no <hi>Chancery</hi> or Court of <hi>Equity</hi> to appeal to for redreſs, but in ſome few Caſes; as in cauſes <hi>Teſtamentary, Matrimony, Divorces,</hi> &amp;c. ſpecified 24 <hi>H.</hi> 8. Matters wherein our Eſtates are touched; but in matters of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, and ſuch Caſes wherein our Conſciences are concerned, we are left deſtitute.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Men are upon this peculiar diſadvantage in theſe <hi>ſpiritual</hi> Courts who are impeached for Non-Conformity to their <hi>Canons</hi> and Orders, in that their Adverſaries and thoſe that are Parties for the moſt part are their Judges. This Sir <hi>Fr. Bacon</hi> in his <hi>Conſiderations</hi> condemneth as a great <hi>Injuſtice.</hi> So that it is evident conſidering the Nature of <hi>Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical</hi> Conſtitutions, and how managed with us in this Nation; how neceſſary it is that ſome Power be placed ſomewhere, by which we may be relieved when expoſed more than others to ſuch extremity of rigour. For otherwiſe as Conſcientious men are more diſpoſed to doubts and <hi>ſcruples</hi> in the way of duty in this kind, ſo to leſs Mercy and Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence from our Superiors.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> That our relief is from the Juriſdiction and Power in His Majesty to Diſpenſe and Exempt; for in his hand this balance is placed, which is that we ſhall inſist upon in the next place.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THis <hi>Prerogative</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> to <hi>exempt</hi> from <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Lawes is in the <hi>Soveraign:</hi> for the confirming whereof, not to inſiſt upon what was acknowledged by <hi>Eleutherius</hi> touching <hi>Lucius</hi> our firſt Chriſtian <hi>King,</hi> that he was <hi>Vicarius Dei in regno ſuo,</hi> in reference to matters to be reformed; or what is mentioned concerning the <hi>Lawes</hi> and Practice of King <hi>Edgar,</hi> and <hi>Edw.</hi> the <hi>Confeſſor,</hi> namely of the firſt <hi>meae ſolicitudinis quieti eorum conſulere de quorum moribus ſpectat ad nos examen,</hi> and of the other from whom it's ſaid much of our Lawes is derived, in deſcribing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:110329:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>the <hi>King</hi>'s office, he ſaith, <hi>Rex ad hoc eſt conſtitutus ut regnum terrenum, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulum Dei &amp; Eccleſiam regat, ab injuriis defendat &amp; maleficos ab ea evellat, deſtruat &amp; penitùs diſperdat:</hi> and much of the like nature that might be urged from Antiquity; but to come nearer home, I bring the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of the <hi>Clergy</hi> in <hi>Convocation,</hi> or the <hi>repreſentative</hi> Church of <hi>England,</hi> who make it ſo great a Duty to acknowledge this as they have expreſſed their ſeverity thus. <hi>Whoſoever ſhall affirm the King's Majeſty hath not the ſame Authority in Cauſes Eccleſiaſtical, as the pious Princes of the Jews and the Chriſtian Emperors obtained, let him be excommunicated</hi> ipſo facto, <hi>and not to be abſolved but by the Arch-Biſhop of</hi> Canterbury. Canons of the <hi>Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> 1603.</p>
               <p>I ſhall joyn with this Teſtimony that of another <hi>Councel</hi> (namely that met in the <hi>Star-Chamber,</hi> 2 <hi>Jac.</hi>) made up of all the <hi>Judges</hi> and Perſons <hi>learned</hi> in the <hi>Law</hi> ſummoned by King <hi>James</hi> for reſolution in ſome <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical</hi> Caſes, whereof this of His Majeſty's <hi>Prerogative</hi> was one; their <hi>reſolution</hi> you have in theſe words. <hi>The King without the Parliament may make Orders and Conſtitutions for the Government of the Clergy, and puniſh thoſe that diſobey and refuſe to ſubmit, and this their reſolution was ordered to to be regiſtred and Recorded in the ſeveral Courts of Juſtice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. And from time to time the Kings and Queens of <hi>England</hi> have <hi>aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med</hi> and <hi>exerciſed</hi> this <hi>Power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. In general, the whole <hi>body</hi> and <hi>ſyſteme</hi> of <hi>Eceleſiaſtical</hi> Lawes and <hi>Canons</hi> are publiſhed by the <hi>Synod</hi> of the Clergy from time to time with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any particular <hi>Parliamentary</hi> Sanction: And yet have not theſe <hi>Canons</hi> their <hi>Authority</hi> from the <hi>Synod</hi> or <hi>Clergy</hi> met in <hi>Convocation.</hi> For <hi>Canons</hi> concluded by the <hi>Province</hi> of <hi>Canterbury</hi> only, cannot (as ſuch) oblige the <hi>Clergy</hi> of the <hi>Province</hi> of <hi>York,</hi> who had no Repreſentatives or <hi>Clerks</hi> ſitting in that <hi>Synod</hi> or <hi>Convocation</hi> that met <hi>Anno</hi> 1584. 1597. and 1603. and yet its <hi>Canons</hi> obliged to ſubjection the <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> and <hi>Clergy</hi> of <hi>York,</hi> as well as thoſe of 1640. where were the <hi>Repreſentatives</hi> of both <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces.</hi> It is therefore the <hi>ROYAL</hi> authority expreſſed in the Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents affixed to theſe <hi>Canons</hi> that gives them <hi>Power,</hi> and they are therefore termed <hi>Regiae leges Eccleſiaſticae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Inſtances</hi> may be produced of ſeveral <hi>Injunctions, Advertiſements, Declarations,</hi> and other <hi>Edicts</hi> and <hi>Requirements</hi> from <hi>Sovereign</hi> Power by His <hi>Majeſty</hi>'s Predeceſſors.</p>
               <p>You have the <hi>Injunctions</hi> of <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. 1547. and Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1559. with <hi>Articles</hi> of <hi>Viſitation</hi> thereunto adjoyned. They <hi>licenſe</hi> Miniſters to Preach, <hi>ſuſpend</hi> alſo from Preaching.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. alſo eſtabliſhed a <hi>Liturgy</hi> or publick <hi>form</hi> of <hi>Prayer</hi> to be uſed throughout the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>King <hi>James</hi> likewiſe gives <hi>faculties,</hi> confirms a new body of <hi>Lecturers</hi> throughout <hi>England,</hi> Preachers that were neither <hi>Vicars, Parſons,</hi> nor <hi>Curates.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:110329:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>Theſe Inſtances altho not expreſs of what theſe <hi>Powers</hi> have <hi>diſpenſed</hi> with or <hi>indulged,</hi> yet are pertinent upon this account. What <hi>Sovereign</hi> Power is thus put forth in <hi>Conſtitutions, Injunctions,</hi> and <hi>Directions,</hi> &amp;c. in <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Matters, may in like Proportions be exemplify'd in <hi>Exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Diſpenſations,</hi> &amp;c. as with <hi>Parliaments</hi> and other <hi>Councels</hi> veſted with Authority the Power to repeal <hi>Lawes</hi> and <hi>Statutes</hi> is as large as that Power by which they <hi>Enact</hi> and <hi>Eſtabliſh</hi> them. For Example, King <hi>James</hi> might by his <hi>Prerogative confirm</hi> and <hi>eſtabliſh</hi> a <hi>new</hi> order of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> which was our laſt inſtance; he might by the ſame Power <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe</hi> with and <hi>licenſe</hi> ſuch <hi>Preachers</hi> which now <hi>ſeem</hi> and are <hi>reputed</hi> ſo to be. And it follows alſo if his Power will extend to <hi>indulge</hi> ſuch <hi>perſons,</hi> it will not prove ſhort in reſpect to <hi>hearers,</hi> which are as it were <hi>new</hi> in the way of their <hi>Aſſemblies,</hi> and <hi>indulge</hi> ſuch as are not in the <hi>Ancient</hi> or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the <hi>Parochial</hi> Congregations of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The like <hi>Deductions</hi> might be drawn from other of thoſe <hi>Inſtances.</hi> I ſhall notwithſtanding for further confirmation, add other <hi>inſtances,</hi> and ſuch wherein you have this Power put forth in <hi>diſpenſing</hi> and <hi>exempting</hi> from what hath been <hi>burthenſom</hi> to mens Conſciences by <hi>Epiſcocal</hi> Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That of <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. In the 4th year of his <hi>reign,</hi> Certain <hi>Proteſtants</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving themſelves and Families out of <hi>Popiſh</hi> Countries into <hi>England</hi> for the ſake of Conſcience, and being not free to ſubmit to the <hi>forms</hi> of Worſhip and Diſcipline eſtabliſhed in this Church, this good <hi>King</hi> by his <hi>SOLE</hi> Authority granteth them the <hi>Liberty</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Church</hi> Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and <hi>form</hi> of worſhip (whereof we ſhall ſay more in its place) as ſhould be moſt ſuitable to their own <hi>Perſwaſion.</hi> This being utterly againſt the <hi>Proviſion</hi> and <hi>Settlement NEWLY</hi> made by <hi>Parliament,</hi> He ſtrengthens his Grant by a <hi>NON OBSTANTE</hi> to the <hi>Statute,</hi> and ſtrictly requires all <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Mayors</hi> to ſuffer them to enjoy this <hi>Liberty</hi> of Conſcience.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Another inſtance you have of the ſame good <hi>King,</hi> in <hi>Hooper</hi> being choſen <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Glouceſter;</hi> and there being certain <hi>Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> eſtabliſhed by <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> to be Conformed unto in the <hi>Conſecration</hi> of <hi>Biſhops</hi> offenſive to his Conſcience, <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. requires Arch-Biſhop <hi>Cranmer</hi> to omit theſe <hi>Ceremonies, diſcharging him of all manner of Dangers, Penalties and Forfeitures he ſhould be in danger of and run into in any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of way by omitting of the ſame, and theſe our Letters</hi> (ſaith the King) <hi>ſhall be your ſufficient Warrant and Diſcharge therefore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>inſtance</hi> you have alſo of what was done by Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> for relieving Tender Conſciences; namely, <hi>Her Majeſty being informed that in certain places in this Realm, ſundry of her Subjects called to the Miniſtry, being induced by ſiniſter Perſwaſions, are ſcrupled about the Form of the Oath, which by an Act of the late Parliament was preſcribed to be taken ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:110329:9"/>to the Form expreſſed in the Act under the Penalty of being diſabled to bear any Office in State or Church: Her Majeſty was graciouſly pleaſed by her Power in Eccleſiaſtical Affairs to give and declare ſuch a ſenſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the words of this Oath, (expreſſed in other words much different) for their ſatisfaction, with a Gracious Declaration that ſuch Perſons fit for the Miniſtry as could not take the Oath in the Parliaments Form ſhould be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted to do it in this ſenſe, and doing ſo they ſhould notwithſtanding be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of her Majeſty as good and obedient Subjects, and be acquitted of all manner of Penalties contained in the ſaid Act, againſt ſuch as ſhould refuſe the ſame.</hi> By which means, many an able man had freedom to exerciſe his Miniſtry, which otherwiſe muſt be laid aſide; which <hi>Indulgence</hi> of hers altho <hi>againſt</hi> an <hi>ACT</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> yet was owned as done by <hi>lawful Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> and <hi>recognized</hi> by the <hi>Parliament</hi> 5 <hi>Eliz.</hi> and her <hi>Execution</hi> aſſented to and enacted.</p>
               <p n="4">4. This renowned <hi>Queen,</hi> together with King <hi>James</hi> and King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, <hi>confirmed the Indulgence</hi> and <hi>Diſpenſation</hi> granted by <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. to <hi>Strangers;</hi> yea, although it was a <hi>Gravamen</hi> to the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> as making an evident <hi>breach</hi> upon the <hi>Lawes</hi> of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity:</hi> for that 'twas granted not only to the <hi>Parents,</hi> but to the <hi>Children</hi> and <hi>Childrens Children,</hi> which were Natural <hi>Subjects</hi> to the Realm, Perſons of great Eſtates, and Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſers of Lands, and intereſſed in the Soil; the number alſo of theſe <hi>Congregations</hi> increaſing, and ſituated in the eminent and chief <hi>Towns</hi> and <hi>Cities</hi> in the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> there to live and <hi>Profeſs</hi> as ſeparated and divided <hi>Bodies,</hi> a <hi>Diſcipline</hi> and <hi>Worſhip</hi> differing from the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> which was not at firſt <hi>intended</hi> as <hi>Biſhop</hi> Laud <hi>complains,</hi> there being onely that one in <hi>London</hi> when the firſt <hi>Grant</hi> was made, and ſuch things were frequently ſuggeſted againſt them. Yet theſe <hi>Princes</hi> were graciouſly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed (<hi>notwithſtanding</hi> the <hi>Act</hi> for <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi>) from time to time to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm</hi> the <hi>Grant</hi> of <hi>Edward</hi> 6th. by ſeveral <hi>Orders</hi> paſt, ſome of them formed as having ſpecial reſpect to ſuch Objections. And it will not be amiſs for the <hi>Reader</hi>'s Information here to <hi>inſert</hi> ſome of them at leaſt.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="proclamation">
                           <head>
                              <hi>The Form</hi> in which Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> confirmed their Liberties.</head>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Non ignoramus variis Eccleſiis varios &amp; diverſos jam ab initio fuiſſe ritus &amp; ceremonias: non contemnimus veſtras, ne<expan>
                                    <am>
                                       <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                    </am>
                                    <ex>que</ex>
                                 </expan> vos ad noſtras cogimus.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="proclamation">
                           <head>King <hi>James, Oct.</hi> 17. About the <hi>Dutch</hi> at <hi>Colcheſter.</hi>
                           </head>
                           <p>
                              <hi>His Majeſty granted their Orders, Liberties,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>in as large and ample manner to all intents and purpoſes as heretofore they have been uſed, tolerated and allowed unto them, any Proviſion or Juriſdiction to the Contrary thereunto in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="proclamation">
                           <head>An <hi>Order</hi> of King <hi>James</hi> under his <hi>Signet,</hi> Jan. 13. 1616. on their behalf.</head>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Theſe are therefore to Will and Command all our Courts of Juſtice, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:110329:9"/>other our loving Subjects to permit and ſuffer the ſaid Strangers and their Children,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="proclamation">
                           <head>The <hi>Order</hi> of the <hi>Councel</hi> for the <hi>Walloons</hi> of <hi>Norwich,</hi> Oct. 10.1621.</head>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Thoſe of</hi> Norwich, <hi>tho born in the Kingdom, ſhall continue to be of the ſaid Congregation and ſubject to ſuch Diſcipline as hath been by all the time of</hi> 55 <hi>years practiſed by them.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="proclamation">
                           <head>The <hi>Order</hi> of King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Firſt,</hi> Nov. 13. 1631.</head>
                           <p>
                              <hi>We Will and Command our Judges to permit and ſuffer the ſaid Strangers and their Children quietly to enjoy all and ſingular,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>without any Trouble, Arreſts or Proceedings by way of information or otherwiſe.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="proclamation">
                           <head>An <hi>Order</hi> of <hi>Councel</hi> for the <hi>Dutch</hi> of <hi>Norwich,</hi> Jan. 7. 1630.</head>
                           <p>
                              <hi>That all thoſe that now or hereafter ſhall be Members of the</hi> Dutch <hi>Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, altho born within this Kingdom, ſhall continue to be of the ſaid Church ſo long as his Majeſty ſhall be pleaſed.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>Theſe and diverſe the like <hi>inſtances</hi> might be produced, which ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently evince it as granted on all ſides, and conſtantly ſuppoſed to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>conſtitution</hi> of this <hi>Realm,</hi> that our <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> have <hi>Power</hi> in and from themſelves, as an <hi>inherent</hi> inſeparable <hi>Prerogative</hi> not only to enjoyn and give Lawes to their Subjects in Matters <hi>Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> (ſuch as are left to the ordering of any Civil Power) but alſo to <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe</hi> and <hi>exempt</hi> from <hi>Lawes</hi> of that kind, tho eſtabliſhed by them in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with the Authority of <hi>Parliament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor do we find that <hi>Parliaments</hi> at any time have taken into Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion what was ordered and done by theſe <hi>Kings;</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> in <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Affairs, as being their <hi>known</hi> Prerogative, no not in the time of King <hi>James,</hi> who aſſumed the moſt in ſuch managements, nor by any <hi>Petitions</hi> or <hi>Addreſſes</hi> to any of thoſe Princes (which is uſual in the concerns of <hi>Civil</hi> Rights) for limiting or enlarging the exerciſe of their Power in theſe Matters Eccleſiaſtical: but rather <hi>recognizing</hi> and <hi>confirming</hi> what hath been ordered by them, as in 5 <hi>Eliz.</hi> and in <hi>Car.</hi> 2. in the <hi>Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity,</hi> and many other <hi>inſtances,</hi> might be tendered.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of Objections againſt this Power, and the exerting thereof, with Anſwer thereunto.</head>
               <p>THere are Reaſonings poſſibly tending another way; the Objections <hi>obvious</hi> I ſhall now mention; having diverſe material Conſiderations pertinent to a more full and clear ſtating this Caſe, which might have been produced in the body of this <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> but are reſerved rather to this place, partly becauſe we find this <hi>vulgar</hi> way of <hi>DIALOG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E</hi> lets
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:110329:10"/>in <hi>Knowledge</hi> with leſs difficulty; and what is required by way of a <hi>Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion,</hi> engageth him that propoſeth, with greater <hi>attention</hi> to obſerve what is ſaid in the <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>If ſuch a Power be in the King, may it not be thence inferred that be hath Power over the Conſciences of Men?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> There is nothing in this Power or the execution of it, but only taking <hi>off Reſtraints,</hi> as to the outward Duties which the Law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth, and the preſſing ſuch things upon it as are contrary to its light and dictates. And the Power which <hi>Protects</hi> Conſcience in its <hi>external</hi> actions, and takes off all fear and <hi>Impoſitions</hi> from it, is ſo far from being a Power over the Conſciences of men, that it is a neceſſary requiſite for acting of its <hi>own</hi> Power in obedience unto God. Neither, 2. doth it follow, that if the King may <hi>ſuſpend</hi> the Execution of <hi>Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical</hi> Lawes, that in the like caſes he may make ſuch Lawes: for the <hi>Suſpenſion</hi> of Lawes belongs to the <hi>executive,</hi> but the <hi>making</hi> of them to the <hi>Legiſlative</hi> Power, which are diſtinct; and in the making of Lawes with Penalties annexed, the Liberties, Eſtates and Lives of the Subject are concerned; but in the <hi>ſuſpenſion</hi> of thoſe <hi>Lawes</hi> no man is damaged in what is ſecured to him.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>If ſuch a Prerogative be in the King, what need Eccleſiaſtical Lawes be tranſacted and eſtabliſhed by Parliament?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> That if His <hi>Majeſty</hi> is pleaſed in <hi>theſe</hi> Affairs at any time to take in the <hi>Advice</hi> and <hi>Aſſent</hi> of his <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> in <hi>Parliament,</hi> it doth not alwayes evidence His <hi>Majeſty</hi>'s Power as <hi>inſufficient</hi> of it ſelf for ſuch <hi>actings.</hi> Such a favour may proceed from a Condeſcention upon the account of a more popular <hi>Acceptance:</hi> that our hands may be faſtened more firmly in obedience to thoſe Lawes and Commands in the forming whereof they have been aſſiſtant. Take it <hi>anſwered</hi> in His <hi>Majeſty</hi>'s own words, <hi>Declar.</hi> of 26. <hi>Dec.</hi> 1662. <hi>to concur with us in making ſome ſuch Act as may enable us to exerciſe with a more univerſal satisfaction that Power of DISPENSING which we conceive to be INHE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RENT in us,</hi> or as alſo it is by the above-named Learned Judge <hi>Hobart</hi> expreſſed. <hi>Theſe Statutes and the like were made</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to put things in ordinary form, and to eaſe the Sovereign of labour; but not to dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate from his Power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>2</label> Powers <hi>ſufficient</hi> in themſelves may joyn, and in ſuch conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction remain entire as Powers <hi>Cumulative,</hi> and not <hi>Privative,</hi> as is evident from what is ſaid in the <hi>Statute</hi> of 31<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
                  <hi>H.</hi> 8. cap. 10. <hi>The King's moſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Majeſty, tho it appertained to his Prerogative Royal to give Honour as
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:110329:10"/>ſhall ſeem to his Wiſdom, he is nevertheleſs pleaſed and contented for an Order to be had,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>by this High Court of Parliament, that it ſhall be enacted by the Authority of the ſame,</hi> ſelf-diſtinct from that capacity wherein he ſtands in conjunction with his Subjects as their Head; in that reſpect being in a <hi>higher</hi> Region above, and in a greater diſtance from thoſe Intereſts, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account whereof his Subjects are many times divided, and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Edicts become formed according to the prevalency of a greater Party, to the prejudice of others which are his Loyal Subjects. Alſo by Wiſdom and Prudence there is a ballance by which the Tranquillity of a Nation is happily preſerved, and one Party not over-born by the other, having this Power to <hi>Mitigate</hi> and <hi>Diſpenſe</hi> (as hath been diſcourſed) with what in his Wiſdom with Advice of his Council ſhall ſeem equal.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>3</label> 
                  <hi>But hath not the King's Prerogative been limitted in our Lawes? are there not ſome things which he cannot diſpenſe with, no not with a</hi> non obſtante?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> I grant it; and in ſeveral Caſes, 1. He may by ſpecial words in the Statute bind up himſelf from making any uſe of his <hi>Prerogative.</hi> 2. In what is <hi>malum in ſe</hi> in reſpect of <hi>Impiety</hi> or <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs.</hi> 3. When ſuch <hi>Diſpenſations</hi> are deſtructive to the great ends of a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, common Juſtice, the <hi>Proprieties</hi> of men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. To the <hi>firſt,</hi> His <hi>Majeſty</hi> or any of his <hi>Predeceſſors,</hi> hath not at any time in any <hi>Statute</hi> or <hi>Law</hi> that concerns theſe <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Matters by any ſuch ſpecial words bound up himſelf; but rather the contrary, as in thoſe two <hi>Acts</hi> wherein more eſpecially our affair lyeth; that of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity,</hi> where that <hi>Diſpenſation</hi> with that <hi>Statute</hi> granted to <hi>Strangers</hi> by ſole <hi>Prerogative-Authority,</hi> is <hi>juſtify</hi>'d. In the <hi>Act.</hi> 22<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
                  <hi>Car.</hi> 2. by the <hi>Proviſo</hi> there inſerted, the <hi>Parliament</hi> ſeems to induce His <hi>Majeſty</hi>'s aſſent in the <hi>recognizing</hi> his <hi>Prerogative</hi> ſo <hi>expreſly</hi> in that <hi>Act,</hi> as if they ſpoke thus, <hi>Tho this Act be very ſevere, yet if it be found prejudicial, or not to attain the end for which we judge ſuch ſeverity to be requiſite, It is an Eccleſiaſtical Affair, and your Majeſty may when you pleaſe diſperſe or exempt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons from it, for we intend not to abridge your Royal Prerogative.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. There is nothing tranſacted in theſe Affairs by the Civil Magiſtrate and as depending on his Authority, but ſuch Matters as in the ſenſe of our Law are things materially <hi>indifferent,</hi> and therefore not <hi>mala in ſe:</hi> they do not bind the <hi>Conſcience</hi> of the Subject in the <hi>nature</hi> of them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in themſelves [<hi>Queen</hi> Eliz. <hi>Advertiſements</hi> 1569. <hi>Preface.</hi>] <hi>The keeping or omitting of a Ceremony in it ſelf is but a ſmall thing, yet the wilful and contemptuous tranſgreſſion and breaking a Common Order,</hi> &amp;c. [<hi>of Ceremonies why ſome are,</hi> &amp;c.] So that theſe Precepts concerning <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:110329:11"/>Matters oblige not in their own <hi>Nature,</hi> as what is either <hi>bonum</hi> or <hi>malum,</hi> but as <hi>Prohibited</hi> or <hi>Commanded.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Civil</hi> Rights and Claims and <hi>Temporal</hi> things only are the <hi>immediate</hi> and <hi>intrinſick</hi> concern and intereſt of all Commonwealths. <hi>Dominium non fundatur in gratiâ</hi> If the juſt <hi>Claim</hi> of a <hi>Prince</hi> may not be interrupted upon the account he is of <hi>this</hi> or <hi>that Religion</hi> and Perſwaſion, nor may a Subject be juſtly Baniſhed, Impriſoned, Confiſcated, or ruined upon the meer account of <hi>Religion,</hi> or becauſe his <hi>Conſcience</hi> is not caſt into the ſame <hi>mould</hi> with the Prince or preſent Eſtabliſhment. It is <hi>Popery</hi> to deny <hi>Allegiance</hi> to Prince, or <hi>Protection</hi> to a <hi>Subject,</hi> upon the account of any ſuch difference.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>Religion and the Worſhip of God being the great Concern of a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is not then to diſpenſe with the Penalties in Eccleſiaſtical Lawes, too great a truſt to be repoſed in any one hand?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Anſwer,</hi> I ſhall endeavour ſomething to unfold, 1. In what ſenſe <hi>Religion</hi> is the <hi>Concern</hi> of a Nation. 2. The Nature of this <hi>Truſt.</hi> 1. How much <hi>Religion,</hi> &amp;c. The moment and weight of a Matter in our Deliberation hath its proportion either as under an <hi>abſolute</hi> or <hi>reſpective</hi> Conſideration; <hi>Wiſdom is better than Riches</hi> in it <hi>ſelf abſolutely,</hi> but not in <hi>reſpect</hi> to the ſupport of preſent life; The knowledge of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Divine</hi> things, is <hi>better</hi> than to know the virtue of <hi>Drugs</hi> and <hi>Plants;</hi> but not ſo in <hi>reſpect</hi> to the ſtudy of <hi>Phyſick.</hi> So <hi>Religion</hi> and the <hi>Worſhip</hi> of God is the chiefeſt and <hi>better part</hi> in it ſelf conſidered, but in its reſpective Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations as to the faculty of a particular Perſon, to <hi>Community</hi> of men for the advance of Civil Affairs, there are other qualifications and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements of greater Conſequence, and more directly and immediately tending to the being or well-being thereof.</p>
               <p>That there be no miſtake in this great Concernment, I further <hi>diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh;</hi> There cometh under the <hi>Notion</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> the <hi>Holineſs</hi> and <hi>Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs</hi> that is of the <hi>Moral</hi> Law, Principles whereof are in all mens natures, and attended in their actings by a natural Conſcience. 2. <hi>Goſpel Duties</hi> directed and ordered by a <hi>ſupernatural</hi> light, no footſteps or Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples whereof are found in us. For the former, Religion in that firſt ſenſe, as the <hi>Knowledge</hi> of <hi>God, Conſcience</hi> of an <hi>Oath, Juſtice</hi> and <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs</hi> in our dealings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are ſuch things wherein the well-being of Kingdoms and Commonwealth is much concerned. But <hi>Religion</hi> as it ſtands in <hi>exerting</hi> ſupernatural Principles, and in Duties termed the <hi>Commands of Chriſt</hi> (as the other the <hi>Commands</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> Jo. 15.) ſuch as <hi>Faith, Repentance, Sacraments, Diſcipline,</hi> and the like <hi>Goſpel-Ordinances:</hi> In the <hi>Duties</hi> under theſe Heads conſidered, and as diſtinct from <hi>Moral</hi> Duties, there is little or nothing directly and immediately contributed by
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:110329:11"/>them to mens <hi>Civil</hi> intereſts, further then where theſe ſupernatural <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues</hi> are planted in mens Minds, the <hi>Moral</hi> Duties of <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Honeſty</hi> do more plentifully abound and are in exerciſe. As thoſe <hi>Morals</hi> do more immediately concern the Commonwealth, ſo the Lawes thereof are principally drawn forth out of them, eſpecially <hi>Second-table</hi> Duties form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and moulding them into municipal <hi>Lawes</hi> under <hi>Penalties</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements greater or leſs; as in the Wiſdom of a State is judged moſt conducing to the welfare thereof. For theſe <hi>Goſpel-Myſteries</hi> 'tis other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, for as they contribute not to us in our <hi>Civil</hi> Government other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than as before-mentioned; ſo is there little contributed by the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> or <hi>Authority</hi> of any <hi>State,</hi> advantagious to the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> but <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection</hi> or being <hi>a defence upon the Glory.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Biſhop <hi>Bilſon</hi> ſtates it well; <hi>Princes</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>command that which Chaiſt the Sovereign Lord and Head of the Church commands; which is all the Power we give to Princes.</hi> [Supremacy, <hi>pag.</hi> 227.] And in the Page be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>By Governors in Eccleſiaſtical Matters, we do not mean Moderators, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribers,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but Magiſtrates bearing the Sword to permit and defend that which Chriſt himſelf firſt ordained and appointed;</hi> but to return.</p>
               <p>If <hi>Adam</hi> had ſtood, all Common-wealths had been proſperous and flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing, and yet no <hi>Chriſt,</hi> no <hi>Faith, Repentance,</hi> nor any <hi>Goſpel-Worſhip</hi> known or practiſed; and ſince the <hi>fall,</hi> you have had well-governed Kingdoms and States among <hi>Turks, Heathens</hi> that never received <hi>Christ</hi> or <hi>Goſpel-Worſhip.</hi> It is with <hi>States</hi> as it is with particular <hi>perſons</hi> in <hi>Commerce;</hi> another man's Eſtate, or Trade, or Credit, or any other <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> concern with whom I have to do, is not prejudiced or bettered by omiſſion or practice of what is a meer <hi>Goſpel-Duty.</hi> If a man I deal with be unjuſt, ly, ſteal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> my worldly intereſt is prejudiced hereby; but whether he <hi>repent</hi> for this, or exerciſe <hi>Faith</hi> on <hi>Chriſt</hi> for forgiveneſs, and <hi>humble</hi> himſelf, I am neither gainer nor loſer in my Civil concern.</p>
               <p>Now it is <hi>Goſpel-Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Goſpel-Religion</hi> we profeſs in this Nation. If then the Duties themſelves performed are of no greater onſequence in reſpect to Perſons with whom we converſe, or the Civil State where we live; the Modes, Forms and Ceremonies of ſuch Worſhip cannot be of ſuch moment or truſt in the manage of them. And let me add, much leſs can there be any ſuch ſpecial advantage or detriment to our State-Concernments in this or that particular external form of Worſhip or Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, that one ſhould be retained by us with ſo much Zeal and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, and from an alteration whereof we ſhould be ſo much deterred; which <hi>evidently</hi> appears in this: how <hi>proſperous</hi> and <hi>flouriſhing</hi> hath this <hi>Nation</hi> been in their Civil concerns under <hi>Epiſcopacy, Set Liturgies, Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies,</hi> &amp;c. and as great Proſperity in other Chriſtian States where theſe have altogether been diſallowed.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:110329:12"/>
               <p>Nor is this any diſhonour to the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> more than to the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> when it was ſaid <hi>not to be of this World,</hi> or to his Perſon or Officers that they contribute no more to the ſettling of Civil Rights and Intereſts, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.13. or to <hi>Goſpel-Weapons</hi> which being <hi>Spiritual,</hi> and not <hi>Carnal,</hi> have no <hi>edge</hi> to cut off mens Liberties, Eſtates or Lives.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>Nature of this Truſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Lawes and Inſtitutes by which theſe <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Matters are to be managed, are appointed and eſtabliſhed for ſubſtance by the Wiſdom and Authority of that <hi>one Law-giver Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> The Application of theſe Lawes, in reſpect of Circumſtances for the well and comfortable enjoying Goſpel Ordinances is all that any Humane Wiſdom hath to do in them, the <hi>truſt</hi> whereof may be placed in the hand of a Wife and Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <hi>Prince.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again there is <hi>Liberty</hi> of an <hi>after-Judgement</hi> to be made by him, that is to practiſe in whatever is in the concerns of Religion commanded by men; Thence ſuch Lawes require not ſuch ſimple and peremptory obedience if conformable to thoſe rules required in the <hi>Word.</hi> Obedience thereunto is with reſpect unto <hi>God</hi> as well as <hi>Man:</hi> if otherwiſe that then ought to be left to the Subject, which the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> claimed <hi>Acts</hi> 5.29. Now altho Matters of <hi>Religion</hi> and the Concernment of it be great things conſidered in it ſelf, and accordingly is the <hi>trust,</hi> yet what of it falleth under the hand of a Civil Power, is neither in it ſelf nor in its <hi>truſt</hi> ſo great.</p>
               <p>Becauſe the <hi>greatneſs</hi> of this <hi>truſt</hi> ſticks generally in mens minds, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when in the diſpoſal thereof it depends upon the will of <hi>one</hi> man, to remove this or the like ſtumbling block, we will <hi>ſuppoſe</hi> failings in the management of the truſt, as great as rationally can be imagined. 1. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe his <hi>Majeſty</hi> ſhould refufe either by <hi>himſelf</hi> or <hi>Parliament</hi> to enjoyn any thing of <hi>Ceremony</hi> or <hi>Circumſtance</hi> about theſe <hi>Externals,</hi> in the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Service of God. Or, 2. <hi>Suppoſe</hi> he ſhould <hi>diſpenſe</hi> with <hi>all</hi> Injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and leave the <hi>People</hi> of <hi>God</hi> to a full <hi>Liberty</hi> in the obſervance of them, and call theſe high defects and failings in Conduct and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; yet the <hi>Premiſes</hi> laſt mentioned being conſidered, there can be no great prejudice to the <hi>Commonwealth</hi> or <hi>Civil</hi> Affairs thereby. Diſtinctly we ſhall weigh both of them. 1. For the <hi>Former;</hi> If <hi>the keeping or omitting of a Ceremony in it ſelf conſidered, is but a ſmall thing,</hi> as was mentioned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and <hi>of ſuch a nature, as altho at firſt of godly intent and purpoſe deviſed, yet at length turned to Vanity and Superſtition, and burdening mens Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces without cauſe,</hi> &amp;c. as we our ſelves acknowledge <hi>[See Preface to the Common-Prayer Book]</hi> and of the ſame condition are moſt of thoſe Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions which have proved burthenſom to the Nation a long time; I ſay if ſo, the not impoſing of theſe things cannot be prejudicial to <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>State.</hi> Not to the <hi>Church.</hi> If theſe directions for Goſpel-worſhip in the external Circumſtances of it, were not reduced into <hi>Canons</hi> and <hi>Injunctions,</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:110329:12"/>but left where they are to be taken up in practice according to the light of the Age, as are Goſpel-Duties of greater conſequence; Thoſe <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> by which States profeſs themſelves to be guided in forming theſe <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Lawes</hi> are intruſted alſo in the hands of the <hi>Goſpel-Miniſters,</hi> for their conduct and direction in ordering Goſpel Affairs; who have <hi>gifts</hi> and <hi>aſſiſtances</hi> from it in ſuch a meaſure and degree as cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected in the ableſt <hi>Stateſman,</hi> as ſuch. And the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Lawes are never ſo well ordered by <hi>Civil</hi> Powers, as when they conſult with, and take advice and directions from the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the Goſpel about them. <hi>To adviſe new Rites and Ceremonies</hi> (ſaith Biſhop <hi>Bilſon</hi>) <hi>is not the Princes Vocation, but to receive and allow ſuch as the Scriptures commend, and as the Biſhops and Paſtors of the place ſhall adviſe</hi> [of <hi>Suprem.</hi> p. 226]</p>
               <p n="2">2. If there were no ſuch ſevere <hi>Injunctions</hi> about the <hi>Forms</hi> and <hi>Modes</hi> of <hi>Goſpel-Worſhip.</hi> (I ſpeak not of ſuch <hi>Duties</hi> of Religion in which mens <hi>natures</hi> are <hi>principled</hi>) 1. The Nation would not hereby ſuffer in reſpect of its <hi>Civil</hi> concerns; but the <hi>Wealth</hi> and <hi>Trade</hi> would be much more proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, the things being <hi>ſmall</hi> in themſelves, and do become <hi>great</hi> only up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account of their being injoyned, and the <hi>greatneſs</hi> of Penalties an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed, being of great Concernment to the State; that is, to the great <hi>prejudice</hi> thereof, as hath been apparent in many years ſad Experience. What is it of moment to the Common-wealth, for the <hi>quickening</hi> of <hi>Trade, keeping up of Rents,</hi> &amp;c. or any particular man's concern as Civil, that men <hi>kneel,</hi> or not at the <hi>Sacrament, Croſſing</hi> or not <hi>Croſſing</hi> in <hi>Baptiſm?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. For the other, as <hi>diſpenſing</hi> with all <hi>Penalties</hi> annexed to <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Lawes; where theſe <hi>Penalties</hi> are removed, yet theſe <hi>Lawes</hi> remain as <hi>Councels</hi> and <hi>Advertiſements,</hi> and being conſulted by the learned <hi>Clergy</hi> in their <hi>Synods,</hi> and commended, are uſeful in the Adminiſtration of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. This is as much as ever was done by the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> when <hi>Churches</hi> were in their greateſt <hi>Purity,</hi> who endeavoured not ſo much to <hi>eſtabliſh</hi> an <hi>external</hi> Uniformity, as to preſerve Chriſtian <hi>Liberty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If it be ſaid, they had then no <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Magiſtrates, We ſay the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> of <hi>Christ</hi> muſt come into a Nation before it be <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> and if it be ſo defective in its firſt addreſs for want of <hi>ſuch</hi> Magiſtrate, and of the means we put ſo great an eſteem upon for the reducing a People, how will the People ever become <hi>Chriſtian?</hi> And on the other ſide, if the <hi>Goſpel</hi> hath a <hi>ſufficiency</hi> in it ſelf without borrowing, to ſubdue a <hi>Pagan</hi> Nation to <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> much eaſier it is being ſuch to preſerve them orderly and regular <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Paul</hi> having <hi>inſtructed</hi> and <hi>councelled,</hi> left his People <hi>free,</hi> and to act by the <hi>Perſwaſion</hi> of their own <hi>hearts,</hi> Rom. 14.5. <hi>One man eſteemeth one day above another, another man eſteemeth every day alike, let every man be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded in his own mind.</hi> That was but a <hi>Councel</hi> or <hi>Advertiſement</hi> in the <hi>Act</hi> for <hi>Conformity</hi> in 18 <hi>Eliz.</hi> given to the <hi>Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops,</hi> and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:110329:13"/>other <hi>Ordinaries,</hi> that they would <hi>endeavour</hi> to perform their <hi>Duties</hi> in <hi>exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution</hi> of the <hi>Act;</hi> it was indeed very ſolemn coming from the <hi>Queens Majeſty, The Lords Temporal, and all the Commons in the Preſent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and in God's Name, and as they will anſwer before God, for ſuch Evils and Plagues as may be Puniſhments for the neglect hereof.</hi> There hath been no want of obedience hereunto by the <hi>Biſhops</hi> being fully <hi>perſwaded</hi> in their <hi>hearts</hi> thereof, as their Duty, of which if they had not been ſo perſwaded, the ſevereſt <hi>Penalties</hi> would or ought to have been in vain. King <hi>James</hi> orders throughout the Kingdom, that the <hi>Afternoons Exerciſe</hi> each <hi>Lord's-Day</hi> be ſpent in examining <hi>Children</hi> in their <hi>Catechiſm</hi> inſtead of <hi>Preaching,</hi> this is only commended as the moſt <hi>convenient</hi> and <hi>laudable way</hi> in teaching of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and that ſuch <hi>Preachers</hi> be moſt <hi>encouraged,</hi> and <hi>approved</hi> of; and how <hi>readily</hi> was this immediately pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed throughout the Nation, and is continued in many places unto this day? In the Eſtabliſhment of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
                  <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. <hi>a Liberty</hi> was left in reſpect to <hi>Ceremonies</hi> to practiſe or omit them according as men were <hi>perſwaded</hi> in their <hi>hearts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By the <hi>Synod</hi> held 1640. ſome <hi>Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> there mentioned were <hi>heartily commended</hi> by them to the <hi>ſerious Conſideration of all good Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as an ancient and laudable Cuſtome of the Primitive Church in the pureſt times,</hi> and notwithſtanding all this extolling thoſe <hi>Rites</hi> (which indeed was as much as can be ſaid for any of our <hi>Ceremonies</hi>) the <hi>Cannon</hi> concludes thus, <hi>in the practice or omiſſion of this Rite, we deſire that the Rule of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty preſcribed by the Apoſtle may be obſerved, which is that they who uſe the Liberty, deſpiſe not them which uſe it not, and they who uſe it not, condemn not thoſe that uſe it.</hi> Canon 7. 1640. And this their <hi>Councel</hi> and <hi>Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> hath not been in <hi>vain,</hi> but <hi>received</hi> and <hi>ſubmitted</hi> unto throughout, by thoſe who were ſo <hi>perſwaded</hi> of theſe <hi>Rites</hi> as they have <hi>commended</hi> them. And ſo would it have been in reſpect of other the <hi>Rites</hi> of our <hi>Church.</hi> And the free ſubmiſſion in practiſe of a <hi>Rite,</hi> tho but from a fewer number of <hi>Grave</hi> and <hi>Pious</hi> Perſons, would have advanced the eſteem of ſuch Ceremonies in the Opinions of others, much more than the <hi>forced</hi> ſubmiſſion of greater multitudes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As a further <hi>Anſwer,</hi> let us conſider the Nature of the <hi>Crime</hi> with reſpect to the <hi>Penalties;</hi> the <hi>Crime</hi> as expreſſed in our Lawes is <hi>a wilful and obſtinate or contemptuous omiſſion</hi> as in 19 <hi>Eliz.</hi> c. 2<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. in the <hi>Act for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> where theſe words <hi>wilful</hi> and <hi>obſtinate,</hi> I would think are not <hi>deſcriptive,</hi> and to be underſtood <hi>reduplicative</hi> as an aggravation, and as if all <hi>omiſſions</hi> muſt of neceſſity proceed from <hi>wilfulneſs</hi> and <hi>obſtinacy;</hi> but <hi>diſtinctive,</hi> and to be underſtood <hi>Specificative,</hi> ſome <hi>omiſſions</hi> being from <hi>wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs</hi> and <hi>contempt,</hi> but there may be <hi>omiſſions</hi> that are not ſo; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not ſo full under the Penalties, as killing a man, and wilful Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:110329:13"/>
               <p>That the <hi>words</hi> of that <hi>Act</hi> 1<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
                  <hi>Eliz.</hi> and other <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Edicts would ſo be underſtood, there are theſe Reaſons: 1. We would not ſuppoſe this <hi>Law,</hi> to be grounded on ſo hurtful a <hi>Principle,</hi> as this, that where a <hi>difference</hi> of Perſwaſion in relation to a difficult caſe of <hi>Conſcience</hi> doth ariſe, that one Party is alwayes <hi>wilful</hi> and <hi>obſtinate.</hi> There is not a greater uncharitableneſs, and more oppoſite to that <hi>Chriſtian</hi> love and <hi>Peace</hi> we ought to endeavour after.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It was not ſo judged by our Governors in that Age when this <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> (<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
                  <hi>Eliz.</hi>) was eſtabliſhed, but a more charitable interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mens <hi>ſcrupling</hi> obedience, as is evident from the relief given to ſuch by Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> who by the <hi>Advice</hi> of her <hi>Councel</hi> put forth a <hi>Book</hi> of <hi>Articles</hi> to be enquired of at the <hi>Viſitation,</hi> and <hi>Preſentations</hi> to be made accordingly: and of 56 in <hi>Number;</hi> there was not among them one about ſuch <hi>Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> then <hi>eſtabliſhed,</hi> that were offenſive, of purpoſe as ſome judge to abate the rigour of that <hi>Act,</hi> and other <hi>Injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,</hi> which ſhewed they were not all <hi>wilful</hi> and <hi>obſtinate</hi> that could not conform. Some merciful <hi>Biſhops</hi> after this Example framed their <hi>Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> of <hi>Enquiry</hi> with more Moderation, and diverſe Miniſters not fully conforming, enjoyed their miniſtry under them; The more ſevere <hi>Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy</hi> obſerving the Liberty injoyed more in ſome Dioceſſes than others, made this Proviſion in the <hi>Synod</hi> 1640. <hi>Can.</hi> 9. <hi>that for the better ſetling <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity, there ſhould be but one Book of Viſatory Articles,</hi> that the more moderate and indulgent <hi>Biſhops</hi> might not have the <hi>forming</hi> their own <hi>Articles.</hi> The moderate <hi>Biſhops</hi> themſelves did not judge that all <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformity</hi> was to be puniſhed as from <hi>wilfulneſs;</hi> nor would thoſe many <hi>Diſpenſations</hi> and <hi>Exemptions</hi> before-mentioned be granted by our Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, if they had judged thoſe who came not up to the Eſtabliſhment, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obeyed out of <hi>obſtinacy</hi> and <hi>contempt;</hi> nor ſuffer ſome of them as Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> did to <hi>Preach</hi> before her in her <hi>Chappel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. That all <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Tranſgreſſions, even in Matters that are little in themſelves, are from <hi>wilfulneſs</hi> and <hi>obſtinacy</hi> (which this <hi>Act</hi> ſuppoſeth it ſo interpreted) is a <hi>Maxime</hi> in <hi>Diſcipline</hi> neither <hi>Chriſt</hi> nor <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Churches were ever acquainted with. <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings againſt Sinners, diſtinguiſheth between the <hi>Sin</hi> in it ſelf conſidered, and as a Sin <hi>wilfully</hi> and <hi>obſtinately</hi> committed, and hath appointed means for the diſcovery hereof; and if the <hi>Sin</hi> be of <hi>infirmity</hi> a different pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, and a more tender dealing is appointed, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6, 7. and not to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply <hi>Cenſures</hi> and <hi>cuttings off;</hi> but upon <hi>obſtinacy</hi> only. We are willing to believe ſuch is (I am ſure ought to be) the Method of our Proceſs in theſe Matters, and what appertains to the <hi>Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Service</hi> of God, profeſſing ſo frequently as we have done, that <hi>we take the word for our guide</hi> in eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing theſe <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Lawes.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:110329:14"/>
               <p n="4">4. Our Law-givers judge the pureſt <hi>Churches</hi> thoſe of the Primitive times, were <hi>voluntary Congregations</hi> of Believers (as we ſaid before out of Judge <hi>Hobart</hi>) ſubmitting themſelves to <hi>Paſtors,</hi> as <hi>God</hi> ſhould <hi>move</hi> them, no <hi>Patrons</hi> then impoſing upon them; now there is no <hi>voluntary</hi> Act to which we are moved, but ſuch motion is upon the <hi>account</hi> of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is <hi>real</hi> or <hi>appearing</hi> good. There is no rational man can <hi>volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily</hi> joyn and become a Member of a <hi>Society</hi> or <hi>Congregation</hi> in ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition within his participation, which is probable to be more productive of Evil than of Good; It will be ſo with us if this <hi>Act</hi> be interpreted <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duplicativè;</hi> that is, whoſoever omits a Ceremony doth it <hi>obſtinately,</hi> and ſhall ſuffer as ſuch an one. I joyn <hi>voluntarily</hi> in hopes to be <hi>edifyed</hi> in knowledge and real <hi>tenderneſs</hi> of Conſcience, and where ſuch attainments are there is a greater aptneſs to <hi>ſcruple</hi> obedience to ſome one thing or another enjoyned, which if we are ruined and undone firſt or laſt (ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere are the <hi>Penalties</hi> in the Proceſs of them) whether Miniſters or private Chriſtians, it will not be with a man (as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith, <hi>If he will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part let him depart</hi>) to loſe the Privilege upon the account whereof we joyned, but muſt abide upon the place and look on while all be deſtroyed: what rational man upon Election and voluntarily will become one in ſuch a Congregation? and this is the real and juſtifyable ground of the Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, upon the account whereof many thouſands of ſober and peaceable Perſons have departed not only from our Communion, but their native Country, for the advantage of that purer and Primitive Order of volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary and free Congregations.</p>
               <p n="5">5. In the <hi>Statute</hi> of (1 <hi>Eliz</hi>) it is not ſimply refuſing or not uſing the forms there enjoyned, but the doing it <hi>wilfully</hi> or <hi>obſtinately,</hi> as was ſaid, for that the <hi>keeping</hi> or <hi>omitting</hi> a <hi>Ceremony</hi> in it ſelf conſidered is but a <hi>ſmall</hi> thing as mentioned before, but when <hi>Commanded,</hi> &amp;c. I grant Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters very <hi>ſmall</hi> being made the Subject of a <hi>Penal</hi> Law, or being injoyned for <hi>State-ends,</hi> may thereby become <hi>great;</hi> the <hi>ſmaller</hi> the matter is in it ſelf, in ſuch a Caſe, the <hi>greater</hi> is the wilfulneſs in tranſgreſſing, and ſo may juſtly demerit a great Puniſhment. But yet a Matter being ſmall in it ſelf, and as it ſtands, the Subject of a <hi>Political</hi> or <hi>Civil</hi> Law, the ſame when it becomes the Matter of an <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Law ought not to be formed with reſpect to State ends, or <hi>in ordine ad temporalia,</hi> tho it be a <hi>ſmall</hi> Matter in it ſelf, and as a thing merely Natural or Moral may not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding be very great upon that account, and greater to the Perſon who <hi>ſcruples</hi> the lawfulneſs of it, than the greateſt <hi>Penalty</hi> that can be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred by refuſal. For there is no Circumſtance or Ceremony that hath a conſtant Station and Place in the Worſhip of God for any ſpiritual and deſigned end (as ours are) but in their relation thereunto are great, whatever they are in themſelves. Theſe Lawes therefore being <hi>Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical,</hi> wherein God and Mens Conſciences are ſo immediately intereſted;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:110329:14"/>the not conforming to them cannot be ſuppoſed a true meaſure to judge of mens <hi>wilfulneſs</hi> or <hi>obſtinacy:</hi> it would be a great reflection upon the Prudence (or the Charity at leaſt) of our Lawes and Injunctions ſo to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret them.</p>
               <p>If the greatneſs of the <hi>Penalty</hi> be laid not upon the Crime materially conſidered, but in reſpect of that <hi>evil</hi> frame wherein we tranſgreſs, <hi>God</hi> only is the Searcher of Hearts; and altho by Overtures and Circumſtances ſomething may be diſcovered this way by men, yet it is with great diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty and uncertainty, eſpecially when we tranſgreſs by omiſſion. The reaſon is, <hi>in Poſitive</hi> acts done by a man, all the faculties of the Soul are concerned and exert themſelves together at the ſame time; and in the Circumſtances of ſuch acting, there remain ſuch overtures of ſuch a frame of mind, as a more permanent and exact counterpart thereof. <hi>Omiſſions</hi> there are oftentimes, when the Soul ſtands as it were, but <hi>half</hi> bent; the underſtanding is not clear, the will undetermined. In an <hi>omiſſion</hi> there is nothing of the man left on Record diſtinctly to be read and conſidered of by us; ſo that we can ſcarcely ſo much as gueſs from what Principles within an <hi>omiſſion</hi> doth proceed, and the uncertainty is far the greater when it is notoriouſly known ſuch <hi>omiſſions may</hi> be from a <hi>good</hi> intention as well as <hi>bad.</hi> To be able ſo far to <hi>dive</hi> into mens hearts, as <hi>diſtinctly</hi> to diſcover intentions is a work more ſuitable to the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God</hi> (<hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12.) then the <hi>Lawes</hi> of <hi>Men;</hi> we would not therefore interpret theſe <hi>Lawes</hi> in ſuch a ſenſe as to render all <hi>omiſſions</hi> to be upon Principles of <hi>wilfulneſs and obſtinacy.</hi> It would be more charitable, where ſo little evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence can be produced, rather to judge the contrary of our <hi>Brethren</hi> and <hi>fellow Subjects.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. This <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> not (we hope) in the <hi>intention</hi> of it, but in ſuch an <hi>Interpretation,</hi> hath been the Argument of all our Sufferings. If therefore that be not the true <hi>meaning</hi> of the <hi>Act</hi> intimated in His <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi>'s gracious <hi>Declaration,</hi> namely, That upon what Principles ſoever men ſubmit not unto it (tho from tenderneſs of Conſcience in the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Evidence) yet thereupon to be puniſhed with the loſs of their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual <hi>Promotions;</hi> but if it appears from <hi>Obſtinacy</hi> and <hi>Sedition,</hi> that ſuch only ſhould ſuffer ſo deeply the addition of further Pains and Penalties as in that Act inſerted, is juſt and equal: If this yet be not the <hi>meaning</hi> of the <hi>Act,</hi> as it ſeems by conſtant <hi>Proceedings</hi> againſt Tranſgreſſors of it (for what man was ever relieved in any <hi>Court</hi> Eccleſiaſtical or Civil upon ſuch a <hi>Plea, He omitted not ſuch Ceremonies wilfully, but of Conſcience;</hi>) I <hi>ſay</hi> therefore, if that be not the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of the <hi>Act,</hi> yet upon thoſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations but now mentioned, there is evidence ſufficient, that this gracious <hi>Diſpenſation</hi> of His <hi>Majeſty</hi> of ſuch redundant <hi>Penalties</hi> (and of ſuch a nature are all the <hi>Penalties</hi> we are <hi>exempted</hi> from in that <hi>Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>) is to be <hi>judged</hi> of as moſt <hi>neceſſary, juſt, prudent</hi> and <hi>charitable.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:110329:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>His <hi>Majeſty</hi> was perſwaded that <hi>many multitudes</hi> (it's his Expreſſion in <hi>Declaration</hi> of <hi>Decem.</hi> 26. 1662.) <hi>ſuffered,</hi> being <hi>enſnared</hi> in their <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences,</hi> and not from <hi>wilfulneſs;</hi> and his charitable Opinion ſeems to be moſt rationally grounded upon an <hi>Obſervation</hi> of his own. <hi>It is evident</hi> (ſaith His Majeſty) <hi>by the ſad Experience of</hi> 12 <hi>years, there is very little fruit of all thoſe forceable courſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>will</hi> is a more unſteady Principle, and more eaſily wrought to a change upon repreſentation of <hi>Good</hi> or <hi>Evil:</hi> But <hi>Conſcience</hi> is more <hi>fixed</hi> and incorrigible; it not being in our own Power to alter the dictates thereof. As to be changed from our Natural State was not in our Power, no more is the change of our Perſwaſions in Matters of Duty, <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> being engaged, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.15. but <hi>God</hi> alone doth it. His <hi>Majesty</hi> therefore wiſely judged it would be leſs injuſtice, and better for the Commonwealth, that all ſuch <hi>Penalties</hi> be <hi>removed</hi> and <hi>ſuſpended,</hi> when the <hi>Executions</hi> of them have been ſo conſtantly miſapplyed, and ſo much to the prejudice and diſquiet of his good Subjects. It is <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> (and not <hi>Ceremonies</hi>) which <hi>eſtabliſheth</hi> a <hi>Nation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>If the Penalties of Eccleſiaſtical Lawes be removed, theſe Lawes themſelves become impracticable. And when Men are left to Worſhip in what Forms they pleaſe, will not that Ancient Eſtabliſhment of our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niform Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Government to be the ſame throughout this Kingdom, be utterly deſtroyed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> For that we term <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> in the Worſhip and Service of God, we find no other in the <hi>Apostles</hi> Churches, but what aroſe from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Principles freely and naturally; theſe Principles being in the ſame, as where there is the ſame <hi>Seed</hi> there will be the ſame <hi>Blade, Stalk, Leaf, Flower;</hi> and there is an Uniformity from <hi>external</hi> Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, as in a <hi>Mould</hi> or <hi>Seal.</hi> Theſe are conſtrained and forced; the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer is from the <hi>Lord,</hi> a work of his <hi>Power,</hi> and there is beauty in it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10. The latter is from <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>States,</hi> wrought by the Power of their Lawes and Penalties, and may have much hypocriſie, but little amia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs. The <hi>baſeſt</hi> metal as well as pure <hi>Gold</hi> will conform to the <hi>mould</hi> into which it is caſt. Such a <hi>Conformity</hi> is no ſafe <hi>Character</hi> to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh who is fit, and who is not for <hi>Miniſtry</hi> or <hi>Memberſhip;</hi> but the other is of great uſe in the Churches of <hi>Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As the <hi>wicked,</hi> who are a <hi>ſeed of evil doers,</hi> are uniform in their Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, being acted from the ſame inward Principles, (<hi>Eph.</hi> 4.17.) ſo the <hi>People</hi> of <hi>God</hi> being <hi>baptiſed into one Spirit,</hi> (1 Cor. 12.) they live in this <hi>Spirit,</hi> and walk in this <hi>Spirit,</hi> (Gal. 5.25) and as in other Duties of Piety and Juſtice; ſo in Church Adminiſtrations, where People are in the <hi>ſame mind</hi> and Principle, they will <hi>all ſpeak the ſame thing,</hi> altho not the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:110329:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſame words, in Preaching and Praying, and Officiating in the Service and Worſhip of God, tho there be no external Preſcripts or force of Humane <hi>Lawes</hi> to bring men to an exact conſcientious Uniformity in the Externals of Worſhip and Ceremonies. Where there are various apprehenſions, this is not to be effected by external force, moleſting men in their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties and Eſtates, judging or cenſuring, or indeed by any Humane Power. God himſelf that can do it, and eſtabliſh men in ſuch an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity,</hi> yet for ends ſuitable to his Wiſdom leaves them various in their actings in this kind; <hi>one man obſerving a day,</hi> or the like Ceremonies, <hi>ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther obſerves it not;</hi> but moſtly ſtanding upon Sincerity in thoſe that doing or leaving it undone, <hi>to the Lord,</hi> that is, out of <hi>Conſcience;</hi> and this is the <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> Doctrine in <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.5.</p>
               <p>That which we term <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> an exact <hi>Identity</hi> in <hi>words, geſtures,</hi> and <hi>veſtments,</hi> Nature ſeems to teach us an example of a Sinleſs neglect of. Tho there be a Conformity in every <hi>Vine,</hi> and every <hi>Figg-tree,</hi> and the like works of Nature, one to another in their kind; yet for the <hi>modes</hi> and outward <hi>form</hi> and <hi>ſhape,</hi> you have not two of theſe that are conformable and growable.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Nor can we ſay, but tho all the <hi>Penalties</hi> (properly ſuch) annexed to <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Lawes are removed; yet there will remain Proviſion ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient left to keep and preſerve men in conformity, and to reduce ſuch (whoſe Conſciences will permit) as are not ſo. For as His <hi>Majeſty</hi> on the one hand hath been pleaſed to aſſure the Orthodox conformable <hi>Clergy</hi> that they ſhall <hi>receive</hi> and enjoy the <hi>Revenues</hi> belonging to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> (the richeſt, moſt plentiful and ample of any <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Church in the World) and that no Perſon (however <hi>diſpenſed</hi> with in other things) ſhall be <hi>exempt</hi> from paying his <hi>Tithes,</hi> and other Duties whatſoever; ſo on the other hand, that no Perſon ſhall be capable of <hi>holding</hi> any <hi>Benefice, Living,</hi> or <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Dignity or Preferment of any kind in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>England,</hi> who is not exactly Conformable. Such Encouragements are alſo <hi>Privative</hi> Penalties, and have brought and kept more to <hi>Conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> than all the <hi>Penalties</hi> removed by His Majeſty's <hi>gracious Declaration.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When was it known that a <hi>Biſhop, Dean,</hi> or double-<hi>beneficed</hi> Parſon, left his Promotion and became <hi>Nonconformiſt?</hi> and that others that have been bred up to literature at great charge, having Gifts and Parts, would be ſo <hi>peeviſh</hi> as to refuſe them, and being thereupon forced to divert from the way of a more free Education, to ſome mean Employment to get a Lively<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, or live upon the Charity of others, (It is the condition of hundreds this day in <hi>England:</hi>) I ſay, can we imagine any men having ſuch En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements in their eye, and the more deſireable from ſenſe of their preſent indigency, would keep off but from integrity of heart?</p>
               <p>His Majeſty, as a Common Father, hath the ſame Affections for all his good Subjects; and never more Prudence and Tenderneſs manifeſted by
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:110329:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>any Prince than he hath done by this <hi>gracious Declaration.</hi> One Party, ſuch as conform, enjoy their Conſciences with ſpecial advantages in Temporal things. The other, they alſo enjoy their Conſciences with freedom from thoſe ſevere Proceedings; and thoſe are ſatisfied alſo. And now <hi>let not any mans eye be evil, becauſe</hi> His <hi>Majeſty</hi> hath been <hi>ſo good</hi> to their Brethren.</p>
               <p>Let me ſay again, that His <hi>Majeſty</hi> hath in tenderneſs and Prudence done a great work, and that which hath lain undone to the diſturbance of his good Subjects more or leſs ever ſince the <hi>Reformation;</hi> That is, in ſatisfying or laying a ſufficient ground for ſatisfaction to the two great Parties which divided the Kingdom in Matters appertaining to Religion; that is in the <hi>Forms</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> of Worſhip. (In the <hi>Profeſſion</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Articles</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> according to the Eſtabliſhment 13<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 
                  <hi>Eliz.</hi> there is an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> in the acknowledgment of both <hi>Parties.</hi>) And this without the leaſt detriment or juſt prejudice of either Party: thoſe that conform en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy their Conſciences, imploy their Talents, and reap the Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the eſtabliſhed Government, without any loſs or detriment to thoſe that conform not; and this Party enjoy their Conſciences, freedom from Suffering, and a liberty to follow their Callings, without the leaſt damage to the <hi>Conformist.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>Is there any neceſſity His Majeſty ſhould exert a ſole Power in Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of Religion, when the Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Nation was herein under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken by his Parliament, and many things endeavoured that way by them, and purpoſes, its likely, of a further progreſs therein?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> For <hi>anſwer,</hi> it will be neceſſary to inſert here briefly a <hi>Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> of ſome paſſages of his <hi>Majeſty</hi> and his <hi>Parliament</hi> in theſe Proceedings. His <hi>Majeſty</hi> obſerving how Affairs ſtood here in this <hi>Kingdom</hi> and the <hi>Diſtractions</hi> that were upon mens Minds about Religion and Forms of Worſhip, and conſidering there are but two ways ſuppoſed ordinarily to reduce a People again to Peace and Unity in Religion. 1. Either by <hi>Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> to diſcourage or <hi>extirpate.</hi> Or, 2. By <hi>Lenity</hi> and <hi>Indulgence</hi> to bear with <hi>Diſſenters:</hi> His Majeſty conſidering thoſe forms and ways of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to which Conformity is now required, have not only been much <hi>ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled</hi> and contended againſt by Learned and Sober men from the beginning ever ſince the firſt <hi>Reformation,</hi> but of late utterly <hi>disfavoured</hi> by a <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative</hi> of the Nation, and a <hi>Synod</hi> of Learned Men: And that <hi>different</hi> practices in the Service and Worſhip of God, had been formerly Patroniz'd and incouraged; and ſuch that were no other but what were received and obſerved in the beſt reformed Churches abroad, and by the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Churches here at home; upon theſe and the like Conſiderations, His Majeſty choſe upon great Deliberation the way of <hi>Indulgence,</hi> it being alſo moſt ſuitable <hi>to his Conſcience,</hi> and <hi>ſweetneſs</hi> of his nature.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:110329:16"/>
               <p>This his Reſolution he profeſſed to all the World, and engaged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by Promiſe to his People, he would endeavour the effecting thereof; which is more than evident in the many Declarations he made hereof, and repeated again upon all occaſions. He was pleaſed in a <hi>Declaration</hi> from <hi>Breda,</hi> to aſſure a Liberty to Tender Conſciences; and <hi>that no man ſhall be diſquieted or called in queſtion for differences of Opinion in Matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, which do not diſturb the Peace of the Kingdom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in his <hi>Speech,</hi> July 17. 1660. He profeſſeth <hi>that he owes his being here to God's Bleſſing upon the Intentions and Reſolutions he had and expreſſed in that Declaration.</hi> This <hi>Declaration</hi> His Majeſty afterwards <hi>terms</hi> a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe</hi> ſolemnly made. This ſolemn <hi>Declaration</hi> or <hi>Promiſe</hi> is ſo much upon his <hi>Royal</hi> heart, that he tells both <hi>Houſes,</hi> (July 8. 1661.) <hi>That ſo oft as he comes to them he mentions his Declaration from</hi> Breda, <hi>that himſelf as well as they might mind it.</hi> In His Majeſty's <hi>Declaration</hi> of <hi>Decemb.</hi> 26 1662. He tells us, <hi>That he remembred the very words of the Promiſes made at</hi> Breda, <hi>concerning Liberty of Conſcience, and the Confirmations he hath made of them ſince upon ſeveral occaſions; and as all theſe things are freſh in his Memory, ſo he is ſtill firm in the reſolution of performing them to the full;</hi> Feb. 10. 1661. In a Speech to both Houſes, <hi>One thing more I hold my ſelf obliged to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend unto you at this preſent, which is, that you would ſeriouſly think on ſome courſe to beget a better <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion and Compoſure in the Minds of my Proteſtant Subjects, in Matters of Religion; whereby they may be induced to ſubmit quietly to the Government, and moſt faithfully give their aſſiſtance to the ſupport of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His Majeſty did not only expreſs his purpoſes for the Eaſe of tender Conſciences, but from time to time endeavoured it: And firſt of all, By a <hi>Declaration</hi> of the 25 <hi>Octob.</hi> 1660. <hi>To all his Loving Subjects of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Wales, <hi>concerning Eccleſiaſtical Affairs,</hi> which mentioning that from <hi>Breda, DISPENSETH</hi> with the uſe of divers Ceremonies formerly enjoyned, that were offenſive. <hi>March</hi> 25. following, he gave <hi>Commiſſion</hi> to certain learned <hi>Divines</hi> to meet at the <hi>Savoy,</hi> and take the <hi>Service-Book</hi> under Conſideration to the ſame purpoſe. <hi>May</hi> 11. 1661. he frees from their Impriſonment ſuch as ſuffered for Conſcience.</p>
               <p>The <hi>King</hi> and His <hi>Parliament</hi> happily joyned in the ſame Pious End, Peace and Union; yet differed in their apprehenſions of the means to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure it, which was our great unhappineſs. The Parliament judged the reducing or rooting out differences by ſevere <hi>Penalties,</hi> to be the means of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> as they tell His <hi>Majesty</hi> in <hi>anſwer</hi> to his <hi>Declaration;</hi> preſſing the aſſerting of the Lawes and Religion eſtabliſhed according to the <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> as the more probable means to produce a ſetled <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Obedience</hi> throughout the Kingdom. The <hi>Parliament</hi> ſuppoſing, (and poſſibly ſome of them perſwaded thereof from thoſe who never would diſtinguiſh between Non-conformity and Sedition) the diſſent of Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts from the preſent Eſtabliſhment to be rather from a Spirit of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:110329:17"/>
                  <hi>Faction</hi> and <hi>Diſloyalty,</hi> than tenderneſs of Conſcience, proceeded accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly. The <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> was renewed, and the Service-Book en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned with no alteration of what was formerly offenſive in it, but ſome Expreſſions of greater difficulty to be digeſted by thoſe that were tender; and nothing done yet in what His Majeſty had promiſed in way of relief to tender Conſciences.</p>
               <p>Hereupon not only multitudes of faithful Preachers of the Goſpel in ſeveral Shires in this Kingdom were put from their Imployment; but alſo the Minds of men are much diſturbed and filled with hard Thoughts and Jealouſies upon this account. Inſomuch as His Majeſty was enforced to Publiſh that <hi>Declaration</hi> of <hi>Dec.</hi> 26. In which he expreſſeth the ſurmiſes of the People occaſioned by this Severity thus: <hi>That having made uſe of ſuch ſolemn Promiſes from</hi> Breda, <hi>and in ſeveral Declarations ſince, of Eaſe and Liberty to tender Conſciences; inſtead of performing any part of them, we have added ſtraiter Fetters than ever, and new rocks of Scandal to the ſcrupulous by the</hi> Act <hi>of</hi> Uniformity. To this <hi>ſurmiſe</hi> and <hi>jealouſie,</hi> His Majeſty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcends to make a reply thus: <hi>As concerning the non-performance of our Promiſe, we remember well the very words of thoſe from</hi> Breda, <hi>&amp;c. and the Confirmation we have had of them ſince, upon ſeveral occaſions in Parliament, and as all theſe things are ſtill freſh in our memory, ſo are we ſtill firm in the reſolution of Performing them to the full. But it muſt not be wondered at ſince that Parliament to which thoſe Promiſes were made in relation to an Act, never thought fit to offer us any to that purpoſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Commons</hi> took his <hi>Declaration</hi> into Conſideration, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented to His Majeſty divers Objections againſt it; and laid it aſide, ſo that nothing was effected thereby to His Majeſty's purpoſe, the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament being otherwiſe minded. And certainly it is not only their Liberty but Duty, to proceed in reforming Abuſes, by ſuch means as are in their Perſwaſion moſt ſuitable and likely to be effectual; otherwiſe they would not be faithful in their truſt. So now greater Severities againſt <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformists</hi> are provided in ſeveral Acts upon occaſion: As the <hi>Act</hi> againſt <hi>Private Meetings,</hi> 16 Car. 2. <hi>The expelling Miniſters five Miles from Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough Towns,</hi> 17 Car. 2. Eſpecially that <hi>Act</hi> of 22 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. intituled, <hi>An Act to prevent and ſuppreſs Seditious Conventicles;</hi> and all very high and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy in the <hi>Penalties,</hi> expreſſed both upon Miniſters and People; His Majeſty notwithſtanding condeſcended to give his Royal Aſſent to that Bill: It being judg'd this Severity was taken up by them from good intentions, and as the likelieſt means of Peace and Union, as alſo if it proved not to be ſo, that they might yet be more fully convinced of the inſufficiency of ſuch a way, having had hitherto for ſome years experience how little <hi>effectual</hi> it hath proved.</p>
               <p>Yet this <hi>Bill</hi> containing nothing for Subſtance but what was proper to his <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Power, being an ordering the <hi>Externals</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:110329:17"/>nothing of <hi>immediate</hi> concern in <hi>Civil</hi> Affairs in the whole <hi>Act,</hi> and His Majeſty having intentions to take the other courſe, if this of Severity effected not what was aimed at, a <hi>Proviſo</hi> is inſerted in the <hi>Act</hi> in theſe words: <hi>Provided alſo, that neither this Act, nor any thing contained there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, ſhall extend to invalidate or avoid His Majeſty's Supremacy in Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Affairs; but that His Majeſty, his Heirs and Succeſſors may from time to time, and at all times hereafter exerciſe and enjoy all Power and Authority in Eccleſiaſtical Affairs, as fully and amply as himſelf or any of his Predeceſſors have or might have done the ſame; any thing in that Act,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As this Act of 22 <hi>Car.</hi> 2. was very ſtrict and ſevere in it ſelf, ſo the execution of it was with much violence and rigour in moſt parts of the Nation; there being Proviſion made in it that ſuch as even looſe, and indigent Perſons may intrude themſelves in the promoting thereof with encouragements, not only of their luſts ſatisfied in perſecuting thoſe they ſo much hate, but their Neceſſities ſupplied from large rewards, for the ſame, having Power given to inform againſt <hi>Juſtices, Mayors, Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,</hi> and ſuch who are intruſted with the Execution hereof, who are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der great Fines and Penalties for omiſſions limited in this Act, and the <hi>Informer</hi> to have a <hi>moiety</hi> hereof himſelf; inſomuch that by the rigorous exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of it Thouſands of His Majeſty's good Subjects were utterly ruined: Perſons induſtrious and diligent in their Callings driven from their Habitations, their Houſes broken open, their Goods imbezziled, the Materials of their Trade, the Tools they wrought with, and the Beds they lay on ſeized, and our Trade every where decayed, Rents of Lands falling, <hi>Poverty</hi> coming on <hi>like an armed Man,</hi> Perſons haled from theſe Meetings for the Worſhip of God through the open Streets to Priſons, being of the ſame Faith with us, and ſo peaceable and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blameable in their Converſation, as that nothing could be objected againſt them, but in the <hi>Matters</hi> of their <hi>God;</hi> nor for any thing upon that account, but their endeavouring to practiſe as thoſe reformed Churches we our ſelves own as ſuch, and hold a brotherly Communion with as the true Churches of <hi>Christ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Nation generally being thus diſtracted and diſtreſſed, thoſe in Power going on ſtill to make Lawes to afflict and puniſh; and others ingaged quietly to ſuffer whatſoever they ſhould be expoſed to for their Conſciences; Matters being at this paſs, there was apparent Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that ſome remedy in the caſe ſhould be ſeriouſly and ſpeedily ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed; His Majeſty conſidering they are all his Subjects, and how much by ſuch Severity the Intereſt of his Sovereignty is narrowed; ſo great a number of his People rendered unworthy of his Countenance and Protection, and upon no other account or crime, but their being of different Perſwaſion in ſome Externals of Religion; Perſons other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:110329:18"/>wiſe for Induſtry, Faithfulneſs and <hi>Loyalty</hi> every way qualified to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> His Majeſty and their Country as good Service as any others of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Subjects whatever.</p>
               <p>His Majeſty alſo did call to Mind that Prudent caution which his <hi>Royal</hi> Father left him in theſe words, <hi>Take heed</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that outward Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances and Formalities in Religion devour not all or the beſt incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements of Learning and Induſtry, but with an equal Eye and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Hand diſtribute Favours and Rewards to all Men as you find them for their real goodneſs both in Ability and Fidelity worthy and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of them: This will be ſure to gain you the hearts of the beſt and moſt too.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was likewiſe impoſſible for His Majeſty to imagine that ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many thouſand in his obſervation, who have ſuffered ſo grievous things with ſuch humble ſubmiſſion, ſhould daily thus expoſe themſelves and Families to ruine upon no other or better Principles than a Spirit of obſtinacy and ſtubbornneſs. Great Sufferings, and by great Multitudes, yet no Tumults, no <hi>reſiſting;</hi> whereas in the beginning of the <hi>Reformation,</hi> what <hi>Armies</hi> in the <hi>North</hi> and in the <hi>Weſt</hi> upon this account, by thoſe of another Perſwaſion, were raiſed, altho yet they had ſuffered but little?</p>
               <p>His Majeſty (as was ſaid) as <hi>a Common Father</hi> beareth <hi>Affection</hi> to all his <hi>Subjects;</hi> but who of them deſerves it, and who not, can nover be diſcovered by this <hi>indiſcriminating</hi> Severity; that is, who are <hi>Diſſenters</hi> upon Principles of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and who of them ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending, are notwithſtanding of a <hi>Seditious Spirit:</hi> Theſe can never be diſtinguiſhed one from the other, when Diſſenters and ſuch as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form not, be it upon what ground ſoever, are all of them equally branded with the ſame mark of <hi>diſloyalty,</hi> and ſo repreſented to His Majeſty, and all the Nation. There is a neceſſity that this Pretence of <hi>Conſcience</hi> be removed, and <hi>Seditious</hi> Perſons diſcovered and left to condign Puniſhment, and others (theſe ſtumbling-blocks being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved) may, by their peaceable Obedience to all other His Majeſty's Lawes, juſtifie and vindicate their Integrity: which can no ways be done while the <hi>Righteous</hi> are thus condemned with the <hi>Wicked,</hi> and no relaxing thoſe Lawes which <hi>ſhut up all,</hi> both <hi>Guilty</hi> and <hi>Innocent,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame <hi>Condemnation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His Majeſty, who hath had a clear proſpect all along of theſe things, and thence publickly declared his avowed readineſs in that <hi>Proclamation</hi> of 10 <hi>July,</hi> 1669. and otherwiſe, to indulge tender Conſciences, hath upon theſe afore-mentioned, and the like weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Conſiderations, been neceſſitated to Publiſh this his <hi>Gracious DECLA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RATION</hi> of <hi>March</hi> 15. 1672. where he hath fully <hi>performed</hi> his <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe</hi> made at <hi>Breda,</hi> and ſo often repeated. Thus His Majeſty, as a
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:110329:18"/>Wife and Prudent <hi>Prince,</hi> whoſe <hi>Station</hi> is <hi>fixed</hi> in an higher <hi>Orb</hi> (like the <hi>Sun</hi> exhaling and conſuming, or ſerving to refreſh, and to ſhew the dark Foggs and <hi>Miſts</hi> here beneath) hath by the <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Liberty,</hi> ſhining forth from his gracious <hi>Indulgence,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed multitudes of his good Subjects, and delivered them from the dark miſapprehenſions of others: Nor is this their great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief in any thing prejudicial, either to the Eſtates or Liberties of men otherwiſe minded; nor are ſuch men abridged in any of their concerns Spiritual or Temporal hereby. His Majeſty hath made ſufficient Proviſion for the ſatisfying their Conſciences, in a careful continuing thoſe Ceremonies and Forms of Worſhip they have been accuſtomed to. Let it not be grievous or offenſive to them that their Brethren have obtained from His Majeſty, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to their Conſciences, the like favour.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>Since theſe Eccleſiaſtical Lawes of Reſtraint were Enacted by Parliament, the King giving his Royal Aſſent, had it not been convenient, if His Majeſty had ſo pleaſed, that the diſpenſing with theſe Lawes had been by Parliament?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> The King and Princes of this Realm, His Majeſty's Predeceſſors, did Eſtabliſh many Things and Orders by <hi>Parliament</hi> relating to <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Matters; but did yet nevertheleſs often ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe their own Power in <hi>diſpenſing</hi> with the <hi>Penalties</hi> (at leaſt) of ſuch <hi>Lawes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A <hi>conſtant</hi> acting with <hi>others</hi> in the <hi>exerting</hi> hereof might (tho no <hi>Preſcription</hi> againſt the King) yet introduce at leaſt into the <hi>Minds</hi> of Men a kind of <hi>Suſpicion,</hi> eſpecially in the Vulgar, that ſuch Proceedings of the <hi>Supream Majeſty</hi> by his <hi>ſole</hi> Power to be an <hi>aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming</hi> an <hi>Arbitrary</hi> Government.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>Parliament</hi> did ſtill continue in this their former Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and firſt Judgment; namely, That a way of Severity was the only means to ſettle Peace and Unity. They had newly paſſed the Act for Uniformity, without any abatement of what was offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive; by reaſon whereof aroſe that general Diſcontent which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we have mentioned.</p>
               <p>His Majeſty being ſenſible hereof, did by that <hi>Declaration</hi> of <hi>Decemb.</hi> 26. move a ſecond time, That an <hi>Act</hi> might be <hi>prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> &amp;c. not doubting their chearful co-operation with him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Matter wherein he conceived himſelf ſo much engaged both in Point of Honour, and in what he oweth to the Peace of his Kingdoms; which <hi>we profeſs,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>we can never think ſecure, whilſt
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:110329:19"/>there ſhall be a colour left to the malitious and diſaffectionate, to inflame the minds of ſo many Multitudes upon the ſcore of Conſcience, with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair of ever obtaining any effect of our Promiſe for their Eaſe.</hi> The <hi>Houſe</hi> returns this <hi>Anſwer, We your Majeſty's Loyal Subjects, who are now returned to ſerve in Parliament, from thoſe ſeveral Parts and Places of your Kingdom, for which we were choſen, do humbly offer to your Majeſty's great Wiſdom, That it is in no ſort adviſeable, that there be any Indulgence to ſuch Perſons, who preſume to diſſent from the Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity, and the Religion Eſtabliſhed; for theſe Reaſons,</hi> &amp;c. whereof this is one, <hi>It will in no wiſe become the graver Wiſdom of a Parliament to paſs a Law at one Seſſion for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity, and at the next Seſſion (the reaſon of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity continuing ſtill the ſame) to Paſs another Law to fruſtrate or weaken the Execution of the former.</hi> So that now His <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty,</hi> had no other <hi>Remedy;</hi> but either, 1. To <hi>retreat</hi> from that <hi>Pious</hi> and <hi>Seaſonable Reſolution</hi> for Liberty of Conſcience expreſſed in Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to the <hi>Parliament</hi> then ſitting from <hi>Breda,</hi> a Reſolution ſo accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to them, as the whole Houſe, <hi>Nemine Contradicente,</hi> by Letters re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned Thanks to him, and <hi>Bleſſed</hi> the <hi>Name</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> who put ſuch reconciling thoughts into the heart of the King. And he himſelf like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>owned</hi> an eſpecial <hi>Bleſſing</hi> from God upon his Affairs, after he had expreſſed that intention.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Of <hi>break</hi> that <hi>Promiſe</hi> he ſolemnly made, aſſuring this Liberty, and had profeſſed to the world upon this occaſion in his <hi>Speech,</hi> May 8. 1661. <hi>That he valued himſelf much upon keeping his Word, and whatſoever he promiſed to his Subjects, and that no man can be his Friend and wiſh him well, who would perſwade him to conſent to the breach of that ſolemn Promiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Or leave the Nation under greater <hi>Diſtractions</hi> and <hi>Sufferings</hi> about <hi>Religion</hi> then he <hi>found</hi> it: And that upon 12 <hi>years</hi> Experience of other means, which extended rather to increaſe the Diſtempers.</p>
               <p>Theſe diſhonourable things, I ſay, His Majeſty muſt have ſuffered and undergone, or <hi>make uſe</hi> of that <hi>Power GOD</hi> and the <hi>NATION</hi> have <hi>intruſted</hi> him withal, tho not with <hi>Concurrence</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> ſo much and ſo often deſired by him, even ſo oft as he came to them: as he tells them in his <hi>Speech,</hi> July 8. 1661. yet nothing at any time was done to his Satisfaction in Liberty of Conſcience by the Houſes, being obliged in their Judgments to proceed in the other way.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:110329:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of former Examples for Indulgences.</head>
               <p>HIS <hi>Majeſty</hi>'s-<hi>Gracious Declaration</hi> contains not a greater In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence, altho it be extended to a greater number of Perſons, than what was granted by His Majeſty's <hi>Predeceſſors</hi> (which before we have mentioned) to the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> Congregations.</p>
               <p n="1">1. There was an <hi>uniform</hi> order of Church Government and <hi>Divine</hi> Service, to which not only His majeſty's <hi>Subjects,</hi> but all the <hi>Inhabitants</hi> in His Majeſty's Dominions were to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, and no man to abſent himſelf. And were enjoyned not to hear or be preſent at any other Forms of Prayers and Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Sacraments, then what is in that <hi>Book</hi> preſcribed, under <hi>Penalties</hi> of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Cenſures, <hi>Fines</hi> to the King, Poor of the Pariſh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>Diſpenſation</hi> and <hi>Exemption</hi> was by the <hi>SOLE</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the <hi>Sovereign,</hi> and ſtands thus; <hi>A Liberty to Separate and Abſent themſelves from the Pariſh Aſſemblies, and to gather themſelves into diſtinct particular Churches or Congregations, to chooſe and ordain their own Miniſters; alſo to eſtabliſh ſuch a Church-Government or Diſcipline, and Form of Worſhip and Divine Service as they amongſt themſelves judged to be moſt conformable to the Scriptures; Eſtabliſhed by His Majeſty's Patent, as a Corporation within it ſelf, and independent upon any Superiour Juriſd ction Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual but His Majeſty; all Biſhops, Mayors, Sheriffs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>to protect them, and ſuffer them quietly to enjoy and exerciſe theſe Liberties, with a NON OBSTANTE.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The <hi>Grounds</hi> and Conſiderations upon which ſuch <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Exemptions</hi> were granted, were theſe,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The Care of <hi>Religion</hi> that ought to be in all Chriſtian <hi>Princes,</hi> and to be ſhewed forth eſpecially in the relief and encouragement of thoſe that are of the ſame Religion, in their Sufferings for Conſcience of their Duty towards God.</item>
                  <item>2. Perſons of the ſame Religion with us, and Sacraments adminiſtred by them according to the Word of God and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> ought to be tolerated in their way of Worſhipping of God, tho they differ from us in <hi>Ceremonies</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:110329:20"/>
                  <item>3. The <hi>Kindneſs</hi> we found in other <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Countries, when we were forced to leave our Native Soil for preſerving our Conſciences.</item>
                  <item>4. There were alſo great Advantages in Matters of <hi>Trade</hi> from their <hi>Skill</hi>-and <hi>Industry,</hi> to the great <hi>benefit</hi> of this Nation and <hi>prejudice</hi> of their own. Lord <hi>Herbert,</hi> Hiſt. <hi>H.</hi> 8.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The <hi>Premiſes</hi> conſidered, we further ſay,</p>
               <p n="1">1. His Majeſty's Proteſtant Subjects to whom the gracious Indulgence is extended, are generally of the ſame Religion with others of his Subjects, and the preſent Eſtabliſhment, in reſpect to Matters of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Worſhip;</hi> in external Forms and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies they are not more differing from the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> then thoſe Congregations to whom the ſame Indulgence hath been granted by His Majeſty and his Predeceſſors, and is ſtill enjoyed.</p>
               <p>And when theſe <hi>Strangers</hi> had removed their Families, and come among us, had not this gracious Indulgence been grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and continued to them, their Conſciences would have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged them to depart hence, and ſeek Habitations where the like Liberty might be obtained. And this alſo is our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, Many Hundreds of His Majeſty's Subjects with their Families have left their Native Country, and diſpoſed themſelves into other Parts of the World upon the ſame account.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If it be ſo grateful a Charity, and deſerving ſo ſolemn an Acknowledgment, the kind Entertainment our Subjects have found in other Parts, when not ſuffered to live in their own Land upon the account of Conſcience, doubtleſs it's a greater Charity to be ſo indulgent to our own, as not by Severity to enforce them for Conſcience to become Strangers in other Countries.</p>
               <p>And for Matters of Trade, the Advantages have been great by encouraging thoſe Strangers. But the Diſadvantages in the ſame kind far greater, from Severity, by which Native Subjects have been ſo greatly diſcouraged, and not only thoſe <hi>hands hang down</hi> that were moſt induſtrious in upholding the <hi>Staple</hi> Trade of the Nation, but by reaſon Artificers removed into other Parts for their Conſciences, the myſteries of our chiefeſt Manufactures have been made common, and others therein equalled, if not exceeded us. A great ſenſe hereof His Majeſty hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in his Gracious <hi>Declaration.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:110329:20"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>
                  </label> It is ſaid theſe be Strangers, Objects of Charity, being driven out of their own Country, underſtood not our Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, they were educated and accuſtomed to other Forms of Diſcipline and Worſhip, in the exerciſe whereof their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences had of a long time teſtified to them.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> It's true, the firſt grant of this Liberty was to ſuch, but in proceſs of time theſe Churches were increaſed and ſpread into divers Parts of the Nation, and this Grant being <hi>confirmed</hi> by Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> King <hi>James,</hi> and King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt. <hi>Engliſh</hi> born, and born <hi>Subjects</hi> of this Realm, they had fully the ſame Liberty granted them as formerly, inſomuch as the Perſons now enjoying theſe Priviledges, are his Majeſty's <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> Subjects.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The greateſt number of His Majeſty's Proteſtant Subjects that have benefit by this preſent Indulgence, have (ſince they had underſtanding) been trained up in and acquainted with no other Forms of Diſcipline and Worſhip then what was found among us at His Majeſty's return, the other formerly eſtabliſhed having been for many years totally diſuſed. King <hi>James</hi> himſelf being educated under other Forms when he came into <hi>England, ſcrupled</hi> many things in our <hi>Liturgy</hi> and <hi>Rubricks. Conf.</hi> at <hi>Hampton-Court.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Finally, it is more <hi>then</hi> a <hi>Century</hi> of years wherein theſe <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Churches have enjoyed this Indulgence, and there hath been much quiet and peace among themſelves, following their Callings without Diſturbance, neighbourly and friendly converſe with thoſe that are of different Perſwaſion in Matters of Religion, no troubleſome <hi>Diſputings</hi> or <hi>Reaſonings</hi> about the ſame, no <hi>Judging</hi> or <hi>Deſpiſing</hi> others<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>: Experience we have found hereof beyond denial, in <hi>London, Norwich, Canterbury,</hi> &amp;c. where diverſity of Practices in the <hi>Forms</hi> of Religion and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip are conſtantly held forth in the view of all men, for ſo many years. And why ſhould not we expect the like peaceable and inoffenſive converſe mutually between thoſe that enjoy now the like Liberty from this Gracious <hi>Declaration,</hi> and others of our Brethren, whoſe practice is otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And the Lord who hath put this in the King's heart, put it alſo in the hearts of our Senatours to be like minded with him. And as His Majeſty hath condeſcended to them in their way for the ſpace of theſe Twelve years (as he tells them,) ſo it is to be
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:110329:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>deſired that they, if it may ſtand with their great Prudence, would concurr with him but half ſo long in the way himſelf hath choſen for the Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of his Subjects in Matters of Religious Worſhip; or at leaſt, until there be the like evident Experiments of the ineffectualneſs of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:110329:21"/>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
